<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vindication of the doctrine of Gods absolute decree and of Christs absolute and special redemption. In way of answer to those objections that are brought against them by Mr. Tho: Pierce, in his treatise, entituled, The divine philanthropy. By Tho: Whitfeld, minister of the gospel.</title>
            <author>Whitfield, Thomas, Minister of the Gospel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 186 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65924</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2011A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222306</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833489</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833489</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37966</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65924)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37966)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2182:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vindication of the doctrine of Gods absolute decree and of Christs absolute and special redemption. In way of answer to those objections that are brought against them by Mr. Tho: Pierce, in his treatise, entituled, The divine philanthropy. By Tho: Whitfeld, minister of the gospel.</title>
                  <author>Whitfield, Thomas, Minister of the Gospel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 83, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Henry Hills and John Field, printers to His Highness,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Pierce, Thomas, 1622-1691. --  Divine philanthropie defended against the declamatory attempts of certain late-printed papers intitl'd A correptory correction --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Redemption --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37966:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37966:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A VINDICATION Of the Doctrine Of Gods Abſolute Decree, AND Of Chriſts Abſolute and Special Redemption.</p>
            <p>In way of ANSWER To thoſe Objections that are brought againſt them by Mr. THO: PIERCE, in his Treatiſe, Entituled, <hi>The Divine Philanthropy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> THO: WHITFELD, <hi>Miniſter of the Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ROM. 11.33.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>O the depth of the Riches both of the Wiſdom and Knowledge of God! how unſearchable are his Judgements, and his Ways paſt finding out!</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>Henry Hills</hi> and <hi>John Field,</hi> Printers to His Highneſs. 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:37966:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37966:2"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle to the Reader.</head>
            <p>IT may be ſome may marvel why I ſhould deal in this Argument which is ſufficiently handled, and the Adverſary ſufficiently anſwered by another hand: I ſhall therefore give an Account of the Grounds that moved me to this underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, which are theſe:</p>
            <p n="1">1. I am abundantly convinced that the Truth which I endeavor to maintain (what ever others conceive of it) is of that conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, that too much cannot be ſaid for the defence thereof; for what Truths are more needful to be contended for, then thoſe which tend to preſerve the perfections of Gods holy Nature, ſome of which, by the Doctrine of the Conditional Decree, are too much violated? Doth not this Doctrine by clear and direct conſequence (as hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhall be more fully ſhewed) make the Creator to depend upon the creature, and the everlaſting and unchangeable Counſels of his Will, to be ſubordinate to the muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="tcp:37966:3"/>motions of mans will? ſo as he can do, nor determine nothing abſolutely and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, touching mans eternal Salvation or Damnation, till man himſelf hath ultim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly determined what he will do: and if the foreſight of Sin muſt go before the Decree of Reprobation, becauſe Sin goes before Damnation, upon the very ſame ground the foreſight of Faith and Repentance muſt go before the Decree of Election, becauſe theſe neceſſarily go before Salvation (which Doctrine cannot well agree with the glory of Gods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ree Grace.)</p>
            <p n="2">2. I know well that the more hands any Argument paſſeth through in writing of it, the more hands it is likely to come into for reading of it: for ſome that will not look into a Treatiſe for the ſake of the matter, or ſubject of it, yet may perhaps do it for the ſake of the Author, with whom they have ſome acquaintance, or to whom they have ſome relation.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I have endeavored to apply my ſelf (ſo far as the ſubject will bear) to the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of every underſtanding Chriſtian,
<pb facs="tcp:37966:3"/>though not furniſhed with the help of any Literature, whereas M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Barly</hi> being to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his Adverſary ſtep by ſtep, is forced to follow him in the ſame way that he went, and to carry on things ſometimes in a high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſtrain then lower Capacities can reach unto: Beſides, he is forced (that his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer may not ſwell in too big a bulk) to refer the anſwer of ſome things to a former Anſwer, which if the Reader hath not by him (as all have not) he cannot ſo readily receive ſatisfaction as he deſires.</p>
            <p>Theſe Conſiderations, together with the deſire of ſome Friends, put me on to the publiſhing of what now follows. I ſhall ſay nothing of thoſe Aſperſions which M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>P.</hi> in his Anſwer to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>B.</hi> did both un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly and untruly caſt upon me, becauſe (as I have heard) they are already wiped off by another hand, as alſo becauſe I well know that thoſe Readers who are moſt ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in their purſuit after Truth, love not to be retarded in their way by any Imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencies, any thing that doth not directly concern the buſineſs in hand.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:37966:4"/>
            <p>I have endeavored to compact things as cloſe together as I can, that I may not tyre the Reader with too many lines. All that I ſhall deſire of him is, that he would not ſuffer himſelf to be preponderated with the weight of words, ſtrong lines, or pleaſing language, which he may wiſh, in the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſer, but onely attend to the ſtrength of Arguments, and incline his Judgement that way where he ſhall finde the weight of theſe to ſway the ballance.</p>
            <p>That this Piece came forth ſo ſoon, was beſides my intention, for leaving it in the hands of ſome Friends at <hi>London,</hi> it was put to the Preſs before I knew of it: and it was expected that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Barly</hi>'s Anſwer would have come forth before this time, it being ſent to the Preſs above a Quarter of a Year ſince.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewel.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:37966:4"/>
            <head>A VINDICATION Of the Doctrine of <hi>Gods Abſolute Decree,</hi> AND <hi>Chriſts Special Redemption.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Doctrine of Gods Abſolute Decree (being ſuch a Doctrine as is ſomewhat removed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the reach of mans natural Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and very little agreeing with his corrupt Will and Affections) hath been much quarrel'd at in all Ages. It began to be ſo in that great Apoſtles time, who was the principal Propagator of it, as appears <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.19. In ſucceeding Ages <hi>Pelagius</hi> and his Followers ſtrongly maintained this Quarrel. In later times (to ſpeak no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the Jeſuits and Arminians, who have kindly clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed their hands in oppoſing this Doctrine) <hi>Caſtellio</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Beza,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hoard</hi> in his PHILANTHROPY, but eſpecially the Author of <hi>Fur Praedeſtinatus,</hi> have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken much pains to render this Doctrine to the world as odious and abominable as may be; To theſe Mr. <hi>Thomas Pierce</hi> hath of late largely contributed his help, in his Treatiſes which he hath put forth, eſpecially in that which he calls <hi>The Divine Philanthropy defended:</hi> I hope he will not take it ill, if we ſhall in a calm and quiet way (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out touching upon his perſon) examine his Arguments, to ſee whether they be as ſtrong as his Words, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their Evidence be anſwerable to his Confidence. As alſo ſpeak ſomething in way of Defence of that Innocent
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:37966:5"/>Doctrine of <hi>Gods Abſolute Decree,</hi> which he chargeth with that great Crime of making God the Author of Sin, and other foul Conſequences, and therefore treads it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his feet with much indignation and deteſtation. And becauſe the Aſſerting and Confirming of a poſitive Truth makes way for the Overthrow of that Error which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to it, we ſhall begin with this, and in the firſt place endeavor to prove, That no conditional Decrees can agree to the Nature of God, and therefore that they muſt needs be Abſolute; and then come to anſwer the Objections that are brought againſt the Doctrine of the Abſolute Decree. In doing of both theſe, it cannot be avoided but we muſt again make uſe of thoſe Conſiderations prefixed before Mr. <hi>Barly</hi>'s Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Pierce</hi> (which the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were briefly propounded, but now ſhall be more largely inſiſted on) becauſe they moſt properly and intimately concern the Queſtion in hand; as alſo becauſe he hath no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> given any Anſwer at all unto them, but onely put them off with a jeer; which whether they have deſerved or no, we leave to the indifferent Reader to judge.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Arguments againſt Conditional Decrees in God.</head>
               <p>BY Conditional Decrees, we underſtand ſuch as where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Condition doth not onely go before the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution or effecting of the things decreed, but before the Decree it ſelf, before the internal act of Gods will, and that purpoſe within himſelf, whereby he hath determined that ſuch or ſuch things ſhall be.</p>
               <p>That ſuch a Decree as this cannot agree with the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Nature of God, if we conſider him in regard either of his Eternity, Immutability, Omnipotency, Simplicity, or other Perfections belonging to his Nature, may thus appear.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:37966:5"/>
               <p n="1">1. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument. </seg>1</label> That which is abſolutely Eternal hath nothing going before it, for it is <hi>abſolutè primum;</hi> But all Gods Decrees (being acts within himſelf, and therefore not really differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from himſelf) are abſolutely Eternal; Therefore they can have no condition or conſideration of any thing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out himſelf going before them: As his Decree of Election was before the foundation of the world was laid, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.4. ſo alſo it is with all other of his Decrees.</p>
               <p n="2">2. All Conditions are conſequents of Gods Decree, therefore they cannot go before it: they are means fitted for the end: now <hi>media ſunt propter finem,</hi> therefore the end muſt be firſt intended by the ſame act of Gods Decree whereby he intends Salvation to men, he intends to bring them to it by Faith, Repentance and other fit means; therefore Salvation is firſt intended.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Faith and Sanctification (which are the principal conditions of our Salvation) are the effects of Election. <hi>He hath choſen us to Salvation through the ſanctification of Spirit, and belief of the Truth,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2.13. <hi>We are cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen to be holy and without blame,</hi> Eph. 1.4. Now theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions being effects of the Decree cannot go before it, for the effect cannot go before the Cauſe, becauſe it receives its being from it; and as the effect in nature always fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows after the cauſe, ſo alſo it doth in Gods conſideration; for his conſideration is according to the nature of the thing, elſe it were not a right conſideration.</p>
               <p>To this purpoſe Learned Dr. <hi>Whitaker</hi> ſaith well,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cygnae 1 cantio.</hi> p 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Cum gratia ſit propter praedeſtinationem, praedeſtinatio non poteſt eſſe propter gratiam.</hi> If we receive Grace becauſe we are predeſtinate, we cannot be predeſtinate for fore-ſeen grace. If God ſhould chooſe men upon the fore-ſight of Faith or any other grace, where ſhould he fore-ſee this? he could not fore-ſee it in man before man had any being in the world, or the world it ſelf had any being; therefore he muſt fore-ſee it in himſelf and his own will, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he muſt firſt will mans Salvation, and in order to that, will to give him faith and other graces that fit him for it.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:37966:6"/>
               <p>Beſides, true Love always flows from true Faith, and by this true Faith and Love we chuſe God to be our God; therefore if he ſhould chooſe us upon the fore-ſight of our Faith, he ſhould chooſe us and love us, becauſe we had choſen and loved him; which contradicts the Apoſtle, who tells us, that <hi>we love him becauſe he loved us firſt,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.19.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That which is abſolutely Eternal, hath neither begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning nor end: but the doctrine of the conditional decree faſtens an end, and a beginning to Gods Decrees: For that which they make the peremptory or abſolute decree, begins not till the conditional decree be at an end, and ſo ſoon as that takes place, this is expired. As for inſtance, God decrees mans Salvation upon condition they will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and repent; now when they have perſevered in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo, then this conditional decree ceaſeth to be conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal, and becomes abſolute; and the abſolute Decree touching mans Salvation begins not till he hath fulfilled the condition; ſo that by this means, Election muſt needs be in time, and not before all time.</p>
               <p>All Gods Decrees are immutable and unchangeable;
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>2</label> they being acts within himſelf are of the ſame nature with himſelf, in whom <hi>there is no ſhadow of change, Jan.</hi> 1.17. Hence it is ſaid, that the <hi>Foundation of God</hi> (which is his Decree) <hi>remaineth ſure,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. His Decrees are far more firm then the Laws of the Medes and Perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, which could not be altered. <hi>His Counſels ſtand for ever, and the thoughts of his heart throughout all ages, Pſal.</hi> 33.11. His Decrees are thoſe mountains of braſs the Prophet ſpeaks of, <hi>Zech.</hi> 6.1. which can never be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: but the doctrine of the conditional will and decree, makes theſe to be mutable and changeable; For,</p>
               <p n="1">1. By this Doctrine his conditional decree, upon ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling the condition, becomes abſolute; and theſe cannot be both the ſame, for they have differing objects; by the one the Salvation and Damnation of all are equally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, upon condition of believing, or not believing;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:37966:6"/>whereas his abſolute Decree is peremptorily pitcht upon one of theſe onely, with excluſion of the other.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Every man in the world is under ſome Decree or other: ſo long as he continues an unbeliever, he is under the Decree of Damnation; when he comes to be a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leiver, then he comes under the Decree of Salvation; when he falls from his Faith (as by this Doctrine he may do) then he falls again under the Decree of Damnation; when he recovers again, he comes under the other Decree; and ſo Gods Decrees will be made as variable and change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able as are the mutable motions of mans will, then which nothing is more unconſtant and uncertain.</p>
               <p n="3">3. When God ſeriouſly wills and intends a mans Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, upon condition that he will believe; when he by perſiſting in unbelief to his dying day, comes to be actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally damned; then either the will of God touching his Salvation is changed into a will of Damnation, or elſe an unbeleever is damned againſt Gods will. If the former, then Gods will is changeable; if the latter, then after a man is actually damned, God doth ſtill continue ſeriouſly to will and deſire his Salvation, though he never attain his will and deſire. Now how can this agree with his moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect felicity, and with the infinite perfection of his nature, to be always croſt in that which he ſeriouſly wills and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires. Beſides, Is not juſt Damnation an act of Gods Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and can any act of his Juſtice be againſt his Will?</p>
               <p>The will of God is an omnipotent will;
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>3</label> whatſoever he wills with the will of his purpoſe, that he works; <hi>For who hath reſiſted his will?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Object. <hi>But he wills their Salvation upon condition they do not reſiſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. How can it ſtand with the wiſdom of God ſeriouſly to will and deſire a mans Salvation in caſe he doth not reſiſt, and he knows certainly at the ſame time that he will reſiſt, yea, can do no other, (if his will be not changed) and he is reſolved never to change it? Or how can it ſtand with his perfection to ſubject his will to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:37966:7"/>the perverſe will of the creature, and to make his moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious intentions and purpoſes to be ſubordinate to the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious motions and mutations of mans will? ſo that when he wills and intends one thing, theſe ſhould make him will and deſire the quite contrary.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If mans reſiſtance hinders Gods willing of their Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; how comes it to paſs that he wills the ſalvation of any man, or that any man comes to be ſaved, ſince he knows certainly that all men will reſiſt? for <hi>whatſoever is born of the fleſh is fleſh, Joh.</hi> 3.4. and it is the property of the <hi>fleſh to luſt againſt the Spirit, Gal.</hi> 5.17.</p>
               <p n="3">3 If God ſeriouſly wills and intends mans ſalvation, mans reſiſtance cannot hinder, for he can eaſily remove it; <hi>Who hath reſiſted his will?</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.19. <hi>Our God is in Heaven, and doth whatſoever he will, Pſal.</hi> 115.3. <hi>Whatever pleaſed the Lord in Heaven or Earth, that did he, Pſal.</hi> 135.6. What is the reaſon that when all men reſiſt, he removeth this reſiſtance in ſome, and of unwilling wills cauſeth them to have willing wills? Is it not becauſe he intends their Salvation? And why doth he not the like to others? is it not becauſe he never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to ſave them? He can do this in one as well as an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, and that without offering any violence to the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of their wills, if he intended the Salvation of all alike: No man can be ſaid ſeriouſly to deſire that thing, the hindrances of effecting whereof, he will not remove, when it is in his power to do it.</p>
               <p>This conditional Decree cannot conſiſt with the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity of Gods Nature,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>4</label> for he being <hi>actus ſimpliciſsimus &amp; perfectiſsimus,</hi> being one and the ſame moſt ſimple and perfect act, decrees all things <hi>ſimul &amp; ſemel, uno actu ſimpliciſsimo,</hi> together, and at once with one moſt ſimple act: There is no priority or poſteriority in Gods Decrees, bu onely <hi>prioritas rationis</hi> (as D. <hi>Twiſſe</hi> well expreſſeth it) <hi>quando ratio unius petitur è ratione alterius,</hi> a priority of reaſon, when the reaſon of one thing is drawn from the reaſon of another: as the reaſon of the means is drawn
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:37966:7"/>from the reaſon of the end. God decrees end and means, and all together; but becauſe in order of Nature the end goes before the means, and we can apprehend it no other way, therefore that order is uſually attributed unto God in his Decrees, that firſt he decrees the end, and then the means, though he decrees both with one and the ſelf ſame act, at the ſame inſtant. Now this Hypothetical Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, which makes Gods Decrees to be conditional, makes alſo a mixture and multiplicity of Decrees. As firſt, that he wills the Salvation of all men; then, that believers onely ſhall be ſaved; then, that this particular perſon ſhall be ſaved, if he believe; or damned, if he will not; then, upon the foreſight, who will, and who will not; the certain ſalvation of theſe, and damnation of the other. Now the Scripture carries on theſe things, in a far clearer and more direct way; teaching that God by one and the ſelf ſame act of an abſolute Decree doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine the Salvation of his Elect, and to give them Faith, Repentance, and all other Graces that are needfull to bring them to it.</p>
               <p>This conditional Decree cannot agree with the perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Gods Nature. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>5</label>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. It ſuppoſeth a general Decree of ſaving all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe this will never takes effect, if it ſtayes here, and be carried on no further, it makes God in the next place to proceed to a conditional Decree of ſaving this or that perſon, upon condition if he will believe, and then to an abſolute Decree of theſe particular perſons, upon fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight of their believing and perſevering. Now here is plainly <hi>progreſſus ab imperfectioribus ad perfectiora,</hi> a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs from the leſs perfect to the more perfect, after the manner of men, which can in no ſort agree to the perfect wiſdom of God, who knows and determines all things <hi>ſimul &amp; ſemel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. This makes this will of God, touching the Salvation of all, rather to be a <hi>Velleietas,</hi> then <hi>volitio,</hi> a wiſhing,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:37966:8"/>rather then a willing, which is proper onely to weak men, who is not able to accompliſh his own deſires, but cannot agree to the All-powerfull God, who is in the Heaven and doth whatſoever he will. Wiſhing always argues weakneſs and imperfection: when a man truely deſires any thing, he would effect it if he were able: therefore it muſt argue great impotency in God, ſeriouſly to deſire the Salvation of men, and not to be able to effect it, yea, to effect it by juſt means: If he ſeriouſly deſires the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of thoſe who are never ſaved, it follows neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that his will is not omnipotent and irreſiſtable.</p>
               <p>This doctrine of a conditional decree cannot agree with the certainty of Gods Decrees.
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument. </seg>6</label> How can that be certain which hath no certain ground or foundation? They make the Decrees of God to be grounded upon his foreknowledge: and his foreknowledge to be grounded not upon any thing which himſelf determined to do, but upon the mutable motion of mans will, and the uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain expectation of what he will do: who hath power to fruſtrate the moſt powerfull influence that God ſhall put forth in the converſion of a ſinner, although he ſhall work as powerfully as he did in the converſion of <hi>Paul,</hi> (as Mr. <hi>J. G.</hi> teacheth.)</p>
               <p n="2">2. This conditional decree hath no certain object, therefore it cannot be certain: It hath not certain ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor certain damnation, for it is equally and indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently diſpoſed to either of theſe: It cannot have both theſe for the certain object, for they being contrary, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conſiſt together.</p>
               <p>This conditional Decree agrees not with the Apoſtles Doctrine,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument. </seg>7</label> 
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.11, 12, 13. For,</p>
               <p n="1">1. He tells us that <hi>Jacob</hi> was loved, and <hi>Eſau</hi> was ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and that <hi>before they were born, or had done good or evil:</hi> but this conditional Decree takes away all difference betwixt love and hatred, before men are born, before they have done good or evil, for it makes love to depend upon their doing of good, and hatred to depend upon
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:37966:8"/>their doing of evil, and that not in regard of the effects onely of love or hatred, but in regard of Gods Purpoſe and Decree. It takes away all difference betwixt Election and Reprobation: For according to this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine <hi>Eſau</hi> ſhall be loved and elected, upon condition he will believe, and <hi>Jacob</hi> ſhall be hated and rejected, if he refuſeth to do this.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Apoſtle ſaith of theſe, that they were loved and hated <hi>before they were born;</hi> but by this Doctrine no man is loved or hated till he be ready to die, till he hath per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevered in Faith or Unbelief, till the very act of his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>The Love which the Apoſtle here ſpeaks of is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of temporal Priviledges, and Hatred of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Not of temporal Priviledges onely; For, 1 The earthly <hi>Canaan</hi> was a Type of the Heavenly <hi>Canaan,</hi> as <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was a Type of the Celeſtial <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> as not onely <hi>Calvin, Beza, Zanchy,</hi> and others affirm, but alſo <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himſelf acknowledgeth; and <hi>Jacob</hi> was a Type of the elected <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as <hi>Eſau</hi> was a Type of the rejected part, called therefore profane <hi>Eſau,</hi> who paſſed away all his right and hope of Heaven for ſomething wherewith to fill his belly for the preſent.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Love and Hatred here mentioned by the Apoſtle are the ſame with Election and Rejection: for the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle makes this the ground, why one was loved and the other hated before they had done either good or evil; namely, That the <hi>purpoſe of God according to Election</hi> (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to which <hi>Jacob</hi> was elected) <hi>might remain,</hi> and that it might appear, that this was <hi>not of works, but by him that calleth,</hi> Rom. 9.11.</p>
               <p>And this holds as well in the hatred of <hi>Eſau,</hi> as in the love of <hi>Jacob;</hi> he was hated before he was born, that the purpoſe of God according to rejection might remain:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Contra Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat.</hi> lib. 1. cap. 16.</note> To this purpoſe <hi>Auſtin</hi> makes <hi>Eſau,</hi> together with <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Judas,</hi> to belong to the Malignant Church.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:37966:9"/>
               <p>Object. <hi>Though</hi> Jacob <hi>and</hi> Eſau <hi>had not actually dont good or evil, yet they had done it in Gods foreſight, according to which God might love the one, and hate the other.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This ſtill croſſeth the Apoſtles Scope, which is to ſhew that the firſt ground of putting a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt theſe two, in loving the one, and hating the other, was not in themſelves but in God: <hi>not of works</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>but of him that calleth, that the purpoſe of God according to Election</hi> (and ſo alſo his purpoſe according to Rejection) <hi>might remain</hi> firm: For if this difference ſhould ariſe from foreſeen works, yet it ſhould be of works, which the Apoſtle here wholly rejecteth: not of works (ſaith he.) Many who renounce foreſeen works as the ground of Election, yet make Original ſin the ground of Reproba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: but the Apoſtle here excludes both alike, namely all foreſeen works from the hating of <hi>Eſau,</hi> as from the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of <hi>Jacob:</hi> before they had <hi>done either good or evil</hi> (ſaith he) ſpeaking of both of them alike.</p>
               <p>Learned D. <hi>Whitaker</hi> brings this as an Argument to prove that Original ſin is not the cauſe of Reprobation: <hi>Cauſa illius odii quo Deus</hi> Eſavum <hi>proſequutus eſt nondum natum,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cygna can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio</hi> pag. 7.</note> non fuit peccatum originale, quia tum aequaliter odiſſet</hi> Jacobum: <hi>quare ſi quaeras cur</hi> Eſau <hi>non invenerit nec acceperit miſericordiam, oportet cauſam aliquam aſsig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nari quae non conveniat</hi> Jacobo: The cauſe (ſaith he) of that hatred, wherewith God hated <hi>Eſau</hi> before he was born, was not Original ſin, for then he ſhould have alike hated <hi>Jacob:</hi> wherefore, if you ask why <hi>Eſau</hi> neither found nor received mercy, ſome cauſe muſt be aſsigned which agrees not to <hi>Jacob.</hi> Now if ſome other cauſe muſt be aſsigned (for the ſame cauſe brings forth the ſame effect) what can this be, but the good will and pleaſure of God, who hath mercy on whom he will, and whom he will he hardens?</p>
               <p n="2">2. This conditional Decree croſſeth the Apoſtles Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, becauſe it makes the difference betwixt veſſels of honor and diſhonor to ariſe from the diſpoſition of the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:37966:9"/>matter, whereas the Apoſtle makes it to ariſe from the will of the Potter: <hi>Hath not</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the Potter power to make of the ſame lump one veſſel to honor, and another to diſhonor?</hi> Rom. 9.21. Unbelievers and believers are not the ſame lump, but theſe are a better qualified and more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined lump then the other; but the Apoſtle makes both ſorts of veſſels to be made of the very ſame lump.</p>
               <p n="3">3. There had been no ground at all of quarrelling at the Will of God, or ſaying, Who hath reſiſted his Will, if his Will had not been the cauſe of difference betwixt one and another. And the Apoſtle might eaſily have an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered (Yea for vindicating the Juſtice of God, he was bound to have done it) that God did earneſtly will and deſire their ſalvation, but they reſiſted his will: Yet he goes not this way to work, but anſwers them by check<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their malepert and audacious inſolence, that dare en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into conteſt with their Creator; <hi>What art thou, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. This Doctrine is eaſie and obvious to every mans apprehenſion that hath any uſe of his rational faculty; namely, That it is juſt with God to decree that mans damnation, who willingly rejects Chriſt and ſalvation when they are offered unto him, and God ſeriouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires that he might be ſaved; and therefore the Apoſtle needed not to have cryed out <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>O the depth of the wiſdom and knowledge of God, his judgements are unſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and his ways paſt finding out:</hi> Rom. 11.33. this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the great abyſs and hidden depth of the Apoſtles Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine namely, How God ſhould hate any man before he was born, or had done either good or evil. To this purpoſe <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith truly, <hi>Eos evacuare verba Apoſtoli,
<note place="margin">Ad Bon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fa. l. 2 c. 7.</note> qui judicium divinae diſcretionis ad opera reducunt aut prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſa aut praeterita.</hi> That they make the Apoſtle ſpeak to no purpoſe, who reduce the judgement or cauſe of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine difference of one from another, unto Works, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther foreſeen or already done. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>8</label>
               </p>
               <p>This conditional Decree cannot ſtand with the abſolute liberty and independency of the Will of God: For where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:37966:10"/>he ſaith, I will do this becauſe I will, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.15. this makes him to will, becauſe the creature wills; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines the liberty and freedom of his Will, to the motions of mans will: ſo that he cannot abſolutely and poſitively determin and will mans ſalvation, till man hath firſt willed it himſelf, by being willing to believe, and to perſevere in doing ſo.
<note place="margin">Pet. Mart. loc. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mun. loc. de praed. ſect. 24.</note> According to this opinion, as <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> ſaith well, <hi>Deus non operaretur juxta ſuam voluntatem, ſed juxta alienam.</hi> God ſhould not act or work according to his own will, but according to the will of others.</p>
               <p>Yea this impoſeth a neceſſity upon the will of. God, which is the fountain of all freedom: for it makes his will and decree to be grounded upon his foreknowledge, and his foreknowledge to be grounded upon mans acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and motions: So that if he foreſees man to perſevere in believing, he muſt of neceſſity determine his ſalvation; and that not becauſe it is his good will and pleaſure to ſave him, and in order thereto to work faith in him, but becauſe he foreſees him to perſevere in believing; and if he foreſees him to do otherwiſe, he muſt of neceſſity de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree his deſtruction, and can do no otherwiſe: He can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not have mercy on whom he will have mercy, and harden whom he will, till mans will hath made way for him. The Aſſertors therefore of this Doctrine, while they are ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitous about maintaining the Liberty of Mans Will, and tender of the leaſt touch that may tend to the contrary, they minde not that they bereave God of the Liberty of his Will, and do as it were caſt fetters upon it; ſo that he can move no otherwiſe in point of mans ſalvation, then man ſhall give him leave.</p>
               <p>This conditional decree cannot ſtand with the infinite and moſt perfect Wiſdom of God.
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument. </seg>9</label> For,</p>
               <p n="1">1. It makes him to fetch the <hi>Idea,</hi> the model and plot, according to which he will frame his greateſt works, and thoſe actions that tend to his greateſt glory, not from himſelf and his own infinite underſtanding, his own wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and skill, but from the actions and motions of the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:37966:10"/>creature. The more skilful and perfect any Artificer is, the leſs he will borrow from the models and plots of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, in any curious work he is to make, but fetch all from his own ingeny and invention: But this Doctrine makes the moſt wiſe and perfect God to ſtand as it were in ſuſpence, and unreſolved what to do touching mans eternal ſalvation or damnation, till he hath ſeen what man himſelf will do.</p>
               <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">Pet. Mart. loco de praedeſt. pag. 35.</note> No wiſe man will earneſtly deſire the doing of that which he knows certainly will never be done; yea can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be done unleſs he affords that help for doing it, which at the ſame time he is reſolved not to yield, though he be able to do it, and might juſtly do it. <hi>Eſtne ſapientis ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis, Deś ne dicam, ea decernere &amp; velle quae caſſa ſunt?</hi> (ſaith <hi>Peter Martyr</hi>) Is it the part of a wiſe man, much leſs of the wiſe God, to determine and will, and deſire thoſe things that ſhall never be, ſhall never take effect? If God wills the ſalvation of all men upon condition they will believe, and knows certainly at the ſame time, that they neither will nor can believe unleſs he works faith in them, (which is his gift) and yet never wills to beſtow this gift upon them, how can this ſtand with his wiſdom? God is able to work faith in all men as well as he doth in ſome, and that without any impeachment of his Juſtice: and if he would have all men to be ſaved, how comes it then to paſs that there are ſo few true believers, ſince none can be ſaved but by believing?</p>
               <p n="3">3. What wiſe man will earneſtly deſire and will the end, and not will the means that tend to it, when he is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to will and to work both? <hi>Quomodo ſapientiae Dei conveniat</hi> (ſaith <hi>Spanheim) ſcire diſpoſitionem neceſſariam ad ſalutem (fidem ſcil.) in nullo reperiri, nec reperiri poſſe, ſine ſuo dono, nolle verò id plurimis dare, &amp; tamen decer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere omnes homines ad ſalutem, ſi iſta diſpoſitio in iis repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riatur?</hi> How can it ſtand with the wiſdom of God to know, that the diſpoſition which is neceſſary to ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (namely Faith) is found in no man, nor can be found
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:37966:11"/>without his gift, and that he will not give this to very many, and yet decrees the ſalvation of all, if this diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be found in them?</p>
               <p>How many thouſands have lived and died in the world without enjoying any means of faith and ſalvation! <hi>How ſhall they believe on him, of whom they have not heard?</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.14.) Are there not many thouſands of the Savages, both in the Eaſt and Weſt <hi>Indies,</hi> in this age (eſpecially in former ages) who never heard any thing of Chriſt or ſalvation? Are there not many Infants of Heathens, that die before they are capable of knowing any thing that belongs to their ſalvation? and can we think that God earneſtly deſires the ſalvation of all theſe to whom he denies all means of bringing them to ſalvation, and to ſome of them, all poſſibility of recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving benefit by the means, had they enjoyed them? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, are there not many to whom God vouchſafes the outward means, and yet denies them the inward work and operation of his Spirit, without which he knows that the outward means will be ineffectual? and can he be ſaid earneſtly to deſire the ſalvation of thoſe to whom he denies ſaving grace, that great grace of Regeneration, without which it is not poſſible for any man to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his heavenly kingdom? Were it not a ridiculous thing for a King earneſtly to deſire to beſtow a rich reward up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a blinde man, upon condition he would read on a book; or a lame man, upon condition that he would run ſo many miles; or a dead man, upon condition that he would live, that he would ariſe and work? And is it not as ridiculous to ſay that God earneſtly deſires the ſalvation of ſuch as are in the ſtate of corruption, dead in ſins and treſpaſſes, upon condition that they will repent and believe; it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as impoſſible for unregenerate men to do theſe things, as for a blinde man to ſee, or a lame man to walk, to a dead man to work. Our Saviour ſaith, that <hi>no man can come to him unleſs the Father draw him,</hi> John 6.44. To come to Chriſt is to believe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 35. and no man not
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:37966:11"/>onely doth this, but no man can do this, unleſs the Father draw him by the inward and effectual working of his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: how then can he be ſaid earneſtly to deſire the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe whom he will never draw in this ſort?</p>
               <p>Object. Againſt this Mr. <hi>P.</hi> objects,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Divine Philant.</hi> cap 4 Page 31.</note> 
                  <hi>That when our Saviour ſaith no man can come to him, it doth not ſignifie that it was impoſſible for them to believe, but onely that they did not believe, as when he ſaith that the</hi> Son can do nothing of himſelf, <hi>John</hi> 5.19. <hi>it is no more then if he ſaid he did no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of himſelf, for God gives ſufficient grace to every man in the world to believe if he will.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Is this ſufficient grace ſuch a grace whereby a man is regenerate and made a new creature, whereby he is born again and hath a new life infuſed into him? if not, how can a dead man perform the actions of life? how can one that lies dead in ſins and treſpaſſes perform a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal action belonging to Spiritual Life, namely, come to Chriſt by true believing? The Apoſtle makes this belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to be an effect of that mighty power which wrought in Chriſt when God raiſed him from the dead, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.19, 20. and therefore for the performing of this there needs not onely ſufficient but effectual grace, ſuch a grace as is wrought not onely by moral ſwaſion, but by the mighty operation of God, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.12.</p>
               <p>This Doctrine of the conditional Decree derogates from the excellency and efficacy of Free Grace,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>10</label> which is the firſt fountain of all that good that is derived to man: For whereas the Scripture makes God and his Free Grace to be the firſt ground of making difference and ſeparation of one man from another, <hi>Who hath ſeparated thee</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle,) <hi>and what haſt thou that thou haſt not received?</hi> 1 Cor. 4.7. this attributes it to man himſelf and his Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will; for till man himſelf by the right motion of his will in believing and repenting, hath fulfilled the condition, and ſo made the ſeparation, there is no difference, no not ſo much as in the minde and purpoſe of God, betwixt one man and another, but he ſtands equally affected to the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:37966:12"/>of all men alike, and when there comes to be a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, a man may ſay that it was made by the motion of his own will, he willingly receiving that which another wilfully rejected, when the other (by vertue of his ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent grace) had power to receive what was offered as well as he: And though the Apoſtle in the former verſes had ſpoken of Miniſterial gifts, yet in this ſeventh verſe he ſpeaks generally of all ſorts of gifts, and the Argument holds ſtrongly from the leſſer to the greater; for if in common gifts, if in miniſterial gifts, it be God that makes the difference betwixt one man and another, much more it is ſo in ſpecial graces that tend to eternal ſalvation.</p>
               <p>This Doctrine doth faſten ſuch a foreknowledge on God as cannot agree to him:
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>11</label> ſuch a knowledge as hath no foundation, no certain object; for before God created the world, there was nothing without himſelf that could be the object of his knowledge, and this doctrine denies that the object of it was within himſelf, for it excludes <hi>Adams</hi> fall, and all other ſinful actions from being within the compaſs of his will and decree, and ſo from being any way within himſelf; whence then ſhall the knowledge of theſe things ariſe when they have no being at all, neither within him nor without him? ſo that the object of his knowledge muſt be a meer non-entity, a meer nothing; and whereas his knowledge being a moſt perfect knowledge muſt have a moſt perfect ground and foundation whence it ariſeth (namely his own bleſſed ſelf, and his moſt holy will and decree) by this means a meer <hi>non-ens</hi> is made to be the object of his knowledge, and ſo in effect he is made to know nothing.</p>
               <p>God knows himſelf with a moſt perfect knowledge, therefore he perfectly knows his own power, and this is the ground of his knowledge <hi>rerum poſſibilium,</hi> of things that poſſibly may be, he perfectly knows his own will; and this is the ground of his knowledge <hi>rerum futurarum,</hi> of things that certainly ſhall be. It is not Gods knowledge that gives a being to things, nor his power, but it is his
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:37966:12"/>will that cauſeth him to put forth his power for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing of them: ſo that not the knowledge of what he is able to do, but of what he will do, is the ground of his foreknowledge of things. If the knowledge of his power did give being to things, then we ſhould have many worlds, for he knows that he is able to make many.</p>
               <p>Beſides, the fore-knowledge whereby God knows things is a direct knowledge whereby he knows himſelf firſt, and all things in and by himſelf, and that <hi>uno intuitu,</hi> at one and the ſame inſtant: but the knowledge and fore-ſight which by this Doctrine is faſtened on him, is a kinde of reflex knowledge ſuch as is in us, whereby we look on things without us, and come to receive information from them, and to have a knowledge bred in us which was not before, whereby we come to know one thing after another, and ſo to have our knowledge daily increaſed; which in no ſort can agree to God who knows all things together and at once, and that in the moſt perfect maner from all eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity: ſo that when fore-knowledge is attributed to God, this is onely <hi>reſpectu objectorum,</hi> becauſe one thing comes to paſs after another, not becauſe he knows one thing af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter another; for it is a moſt true rule, That <hi>Deo omnia praeſentia ſunt in ſua aeternitate, etiam praeterita &amp; futura,</hi> as he is God from everlaſting to everlaſting, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90. ſo he is an all-knowing God from everlaſting to everlaſting and that without any variation, his knowledge not really differing from himſelf.</p>
               <p>Laſtly,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>12</label> If the glory of God by the merciful Salvation of ſome, and juſt Condemnation of others, be laſt in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, then they were firſt in intention, and therefore before the foreſight of ſin. This is an Argument often urged by Dr. <hi>Twiſs,</hi> to ſhew the incongruity of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional Decree, whereby the foreſight of ſomething done in time, is put before that which was before all time, namely, Gods everlaſting Decree.
<note place="margin">C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p. 3. Page <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7.</note> This indeed Mr. <hi>P</hi> vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifies, as that which raw Sophiſters in the Schools would be aſhamed of, and with much confidence tells us he will
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:37966:13"/>demonſtrate this Rule to be falſe, when ever it ſhall be required of him. To which we may anſwer with as much confidence, Let him do it if he can. Let him demonſtrate if he can that this old Maxim in Logick <hi>(Quod primum eſt in intentione, ultimum eſt in executione)</hi> is falſe, if rightly underſtood; if underſtood as Dr. <hi>Twiſs</hi> underſtands and applies it, namely, <hi>De finibus ultimis non intermediis,</hi> as it is taken in this Argument. That Doctors known skill in arguing, deſerved a more modeſt cenſure at his hands. As for the Inſtance he brings to diſprove this Maxim, we ſhall not wrong it to ſay it is ridiculous; For (ſaith he) he that firſt intends to take ſhip at <hi>Dover,</hi> and after ſayl into <hi>France,</hi> muſt by this Argument firſt ſayl into <hi>France,</hi> and afterwards take ſhip at <hi>Dover: Cujus contrarium verum eſt;</hi> for is not the journey into <hi>France</hi> the firſt thing here intended, and in order to that to take ſhip at <hi>Dover?</hi> If Mr. <hi>P.</hi> hath no ſtronger demonſtrations then theſe, they will not much daunt his Oppoſites; but over-much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence may ſometimes dazle the eyes of thoſe who are quickeſt ſighted.</p>
               <p>But to adde a little more ſtrength to this Argument, Mr. <hi>P.</hi> doth not deny that God doth permit ſin; if he doth permit ſin to be, he doth not permit it againſt his will; and if he wills to permit it, what reaſon can be brought why he ſhould will to permit it, but that hereby he might make way for the manifeſtation of the glory of his mercy in the merciful Salvation of ſome, and of his ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice in the juſt Damnation of others (neither of which could have been done if ſin had never been) therefore both theſe muſt needs be determined before the permiſsion of ſin, without which there could be no foreſight of it; for how was it poſsible for God to foreſee that ſin ſhould be, before he willed to permit that ſin might be?</p>
               <p>Thus we have done with confirmation of the poſitive Truth; it follows now that we endeavour to give ſome ſatisfaction to thoſe difficulties that are objected againſt it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:37966:13"/>
               <head>Anſwers to ſuch Objections as are brought againſt Gods Abſolute Decree.</head>
               <p>BEfore we come to give anſwer to the particular Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, theſe things may be propounded in general in way of Anſwer.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is very agreeable to right reaſon, that God being a moſt free, abſolute and omnipotent Agent, he might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign the creatures that were of his own making to what ends himſelf pleaſed, without giving account to any. <hi>Why doſt thou ſtrive againſt him, for he doth not give account of his matters?</hi> Job 33.15. It was in his power and his own choice, whether he would make them or not make them, and when he did make them, he made them for his own glory, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.4. therefore he might appoint them to ſuch ends as ſhould make moſt for his glory.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That which the Scripture plainly, clearly and poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively aſſerteth that God doth, we ought not to deny that he doth it, though we cannot diſcern the maner how he doth it. It rather beſeems us humbly to acknowledge our ignorance in apprehending the maner of his working, then to deny any of his works, then to deny that he worketh all things according to the good pleaſure of his will, or to deny that a ſparrow falls not to the ground, or an hair from our head without the will of the Father, or that he worketh moſt determinately, certainly and infallibly in the various and mutable motions of mans will: yea, moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lily, juſtly and righteouſly in thoſe very actions, wherein man works moſt perverſly, unjuſtly and unrighteouſly, how elſe can it be ſaid when <hi>Joſephs</hi> brethren ſold him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Egypt</hi> out of envy, that <hi>God ſent a man before?</hi> &amp;c. and vvhen <hi>David</hi> numbred the people, it is ſaid not onely that Satan ſtood againſt <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and provoked <hi>David</hi> to num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the people, 1 <hi>Chr.</hi> 21.1. but that the <hi>Lord moved</hi> David <hi>againſt them, in that he ſaid, Go number</hi> Iſrael, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.1.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:37966:14"/>
                  <hi>Miro &amp; ineffabili modo,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Euchirid. ad Laurent. cap.</hi> 100.</note> id non fit praeter voluntatem Dei, quod fit contra voluntatem ejus</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auſtin.</hi>)</p>
               <p n="3">3. The ſum of what Mr. <hi>P.</hi> or any of his predeceſſors in this Controverſie about Gods abſolute Decree hath objected againſt it, is included in that which the Apoſtle objects againſt himſelf, ſpeaking of this ſubject, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.14. <hi>Is God unjuſt?</hi> and <hi>who hath reſiſted his will?</hi> Which he anſwers with an <hi>Abſit,</hi> and, <hi>Quis tu es? God forbid that there ſhould be any unrighteouſneſs in him,</hi> and, <hi>Who art thou, O man, that pleadeſt with God?</hi> vouchſafing no other an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer but this, whereby he gives a ſharp check to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lepert boldneſs and audacious inſolence of thoſe that ſhall dare thus to quarrel with their Creator, as if the ſheard ſhould ſtrive with the Potter: And if we ſhould give no other anſwer but this (having the great Apoſtle for our example) it might ſuffice. But for further ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we ſhall endeavor to give a particular anſwer to the particular objections, that it may appear we deſire not to decline any thing that carries with it any weight of truth.</p>
               <p>Object. 1. <hi>The firſt and principal Objection againſt the Doctrine of the abſolute Decree, is, That it makes God is be the Author of ſin: For if in the firſt place he decrees to glorifie his Juſtice in the juſt condemnation of ſome men (which is the decree of Reprobation) then it follows, that in order to this, he muſt decree the permiſſiin of ſin, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which there can be no juſt condemnation; and if he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees the being of ſin, then he is the author of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> For anſwer, It cannot be denied that God doth permit ſin: for if he did not permit it, he could ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily hinder it; ſo that without his permiſſion, ſin could not be.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If he doth permit it, he hath decreed to permit it; for he works by counſel, and what he doth in time, he hath determined before all time: And the Scripture is plain, that God decrees thoſe actions, which when men do, they do very ſinfully. What worſe action then the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:37966:14"/>crucifying of Chriſt? yet it is ſaid, <hi>he was delivered by the determinate counſel and foreknowledge of God,</hi> Acts 2.23. here is not onely knowledge, but a determination of the thing to be done. And it is ſaid, That <hi>Herod, Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat and the Jews, did that to</hi> Chriſt when they crucified him, <hi>which the hand of God and his Counſel had determined before to be done,</hi> cap. 4.27, 28. Beſides, if God doth permit ſin, he doth willingly permit it; otherwiſe it ſhould come to paſs whether he will or not,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Enchirid.</hi> cap. 95.</note> and ſo he ſhould not be omnipotent. <hi>Nihil fit</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auſtin) niſi quod omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potens fieri velit, vel ipſe faciendo, vel ab aliis fieri permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. But though God hath decreed that ſin ſhall be, and therefore hath decreed to permit it, without which it could not be; yet it doth not follow that he is the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of it.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>But if he hath willed and decreed it,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ad ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam collat. Vorſt</hi> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ct. 17.</note> his decree is an energetical operative decree, therefore he hath ſome hand in working and effecting of it, as</hi> Calvin, Piſcator <hi>and others teach, who are for the abſolute decree.</hi> Negari non poteſt, illum aliquo modo procurare negotium, cujus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilio &amp; decreto negotium geritur, <hi>ſaith</hi> Piſcator. <hi>And if his decree be operative, ſo as he hath any hand at all in the working of it, then he muſt needs be the Author of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> For anſwer of this, Two things are to be clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: 1. That Gods permiſſion is not ſuch a bare permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion as is without all action and operation.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That though his permiſſion be accompanied with ſome kinde of operation, yet he is no author of evil.</p>
               <p>That Gods permiſſion of ſin is accompanied with ſome kinde of operation, appears,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>1</label> Becauſe when he permits ſin, he doth <hi>volens permittere,</hi> he doth willingly permit it, elſe it ſhould be againſt his will;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſt in Enchirid. ad Laurent.</hi> cap. 100.</note> which cannot be (as was ſhewed) If he doth willingly permit it, then there is ſome act of his will about it: <hi>Deus permittit</hi> (ſaith <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin) aut volens, aut nolens &amp; in vitus; non certè invitus, quia id eſſet cum triſtitia, &amp; potentia ſe majorem haberet;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:37966:15"/>ſi voleus permittit, eſt genus quoddam voluntatis.</hi> Here <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> grants that God hath ſome kinde of will in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſin, if any kinde of will, this muſt needs be a perfect will, for no imperfect will agrees to God, who is perfection it ſelf: And how can he be ſaid to will any thing without any act of his will?</p>
               <p>Scripture-expreſſions do conſtantly hold forth Gods maner of working in ſin,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>2</label> by way of action: It doth not ſay that God ſuffered <hi>Joſephs</hi> brethren to ſell him into <hi>Egypt,</hi> but that <hi>God ſent him. It was not you that ſent me hither, but God.</hi> Gen. 45.8. It doth not ſay that God ſuffered <hi>Pharaoh</hi> to harden his own heart, but that <hi>God hardned it,</hi> Exod. 9.12. That he ſuffered the Canaanites to harden their hearts againſt <hi>Iſrael;</hi> but <hi>it was of the Lord that they ſhould harden their hearts againſt them, that he might deſtroy them.</hi> Joſh. 11.20. That he ſuffered <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolom</hi> to defile his fathers concubines; but he tells <hi>David, What thou haſt done in ſecret, I will do in the ſight of this Sun,</hi> 2 Sam. 12.12. So it is ſaid, that <hi>God bade Shimei curſe David.</hi> That he bade the evil ſpirit <hi>go and deceive Ahab,</hi> 1 King. 29.22. Go forth and do ſo. <hi>Job</hi> ſaith that <hi>God had taken away his</hi> cattel, when the Caldeans and Sabeans took them away. <hi>Job.</hi> 1. The Prophet complains that the <hi>Lord had hardned their hearts againſt his fear,</hi> Iſa. 63.13. It is ſaid, that the <hi>Lord turned the hearts of the Egyptians to hate his people,</hi> Pſal. 105.35. That when the falſe Prophet was deceived, <hi>he had deceived</hi> them. Ezek. 14.9. That he <hi>gave up the Gentiles to vile luſts.</hi> Rom. 1.26. That he <hi>ſmote the Jews with the ſpirit of ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> that they ſhould not ſee with their eyes, nor hear with their ears. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.8, 9. That <hi>he would ſend to thoſe that loved not the truth, ſtrong deluſions, that they ſhould believe lies.</hi> 2 Theſ. 2.10, 11. That <hi>God put into the hearts of the ten Kings, to give their power to the beaſt.</hi> Rev. 17.17. and many other like places there are that ſpeak in the ſame kinde of language. Now can we think that when the Scripture doth in ſo many places, and ſo conſtantly ſet forth the maner of Gods working in ſin, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y ſuch expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:37966:15"/>as denote action, and very ſeldom (if at all) as ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie a bare permiſſion onely; as that in the ſelling of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> into <hi>Egypt,</hi> in <hi>Pharaohs</hi> refuſing to let the people go, and the reſt before named; God ſhould exerciſe a bare permiſsion onely, without any action, that he ſhould ſit ſtill as a Spectator without doing any thing at all.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>To theſe places Mr.</hi> P. <hi>anſwereth,
<note place="margin">Cap. 4. pag. 48.</note> That by a common Hebraiſm, verbs active in ſound, are onely permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive in ſignification.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This indeed he dictates, but he doth not demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, nor bring the leaſt patch of an Argument to prove it, neither will all his skill in the Hebrew, enable him to do it; and may he not by this ſhift evade the cleareſt and ſtrongeſt Scriptures that are brought againſt him, by tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling us that they ſignifie quite another thing then the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the words do import, if we will believe him?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Why may we not then interpret other Scriptures in the like maner, where the like expreſſions are uſed; as when the Lord ſaith, <hi>I form the light, and create darkneſs, I make peace, and create evil.</hi> Iſa. 45.7. <hi>I have made the earth, and created man upon it, my hands ſpread out the heavens. Pſal.</hi> 12. Why may we not by Mr. <hi>P.</hi> his He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braiſms, interpret theſe verbs that are active in ſound, to be permiſsive onely in ſignification, and ſay that God hath permitted light and darkneſs to be created, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered the earth to be made, and the heavens to be ſpread out?</p>
               <p>Object. But he further objects, <hi>That theſe expreſſions cannot be properly taken, therefore they do not denote any action but onely permiſſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Though they cannot be ſo properly taken, as to ſignifie that God worketh in the ſame maner in evil acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as he doth in good, or as evil men themſelves do, yet neither ſo improperly as to ſignifie a bare permiſſion without any action at all, and though we be not able to apprehend his ſecret and wonderful maner of working in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:37966:16"/>evil actions; yet neither are we to deny that he hath any work at all in them, ſince himſelf doth ſo often and ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly affirm it; though he doth it <hi>miro &amp; ineffabili mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do</hi> (as <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeaks) yet we are not to deny the doing of it. And by thoſe former Scriptures mentioned, it may appear what little reaſon Mr. <hi>P.</hi> had to make ſuch a cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor againſt thoſe our Proteſtant Divines (ſome of which God uſed as principal inſtruments in advancing that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious work of Reformation) as if they made God to be the Author of ſin; when he knows that they poſitively profeſſed, and ſome of them ſtrongly proved the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; and what expreſsions they uſed in this ſubject, were but the ſame in effect with Scripture expreſsions, yea not altogether ſo high: Yet he labors, <hi>magno conatu,</hi> to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain this charge againſt them, herein complying with the Papiſts; ſo that <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himſelf is not more eager and induſtrious in carrying on this charge againſt <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Zuinglius,</hi> then he is in carrying it on, both againſt theſe and many others, arraigning no leſs then twelve of them as guilty of the great ſin of Blaſphemy, by making God the Author of ſin, when they ſpeak but the very ſame things for ſubſtance which the Scripture ſpeaks about it; as if it were his drift and deſign to make them and their doctrine odious.</p>
               <p>That God hath ſome hand in the acts of ſinful men, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>3</label> becauſe the <hi>Subſtratum</hi> or ſubject of ſin, namely, the natural motion or action whereto ſin cleaves, is that whereof he is the proper cauſe and efficient: therefore he muſt needs have ſome efficiency in it.</p>
               <p>Object. Againſt this Mr. <hi>P.</hi> objects, <hi>That it is as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to ſeparate the wickedneſs of the act, from the act which is wicked, as to ſeparate roundneſs from the Globe, and to ſeparate ſinfulneſs from the ſin,
<note place="margin">Cap 4. pag. 48.</note> as from the ſinful act.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> God is little beholding to him for ſo denying him to be the Author of the evil that cleaves to the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of nature, as withall, to deny him to be the Author
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:37966:16"/>of Nature, for maintaining his Purity, by denying his Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotency.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Doth not the Scripture tell us expreſly, that <hi>in him we live, move and have our being?</hi> Acts 17.25. As he is the Author of our being, ſo alſo of all thoſe natural motions and actions that ariſe from our being; as we cannot live without him, ſo we cannot move without him. As we cannot move our hand or foot, ſo not our heart or tongue without him. <hi>Omnes cauſae ſecundae ſicut dependent à Deo in eſſe, it a dependent ab eo in operari.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Was not Natures work the ſame in <hi>Adam,</hi> when he ate the forbidden fruit as when he did his neceſſary food, and in <hi>David</hi> (which is his own inſtance) when he lay with <hi>Bathſheba,</hi> as when he lay with his lawful wife? in an Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioner when he murders a man out of malice, as when he kills a man by the command of the Magiſtrate? It is a true Rule, That <hi>Deus agit iu peccato, non tanquam cauſa mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, ſed tanquam cauſa naturalis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Every new action and motion is a new entity, now all entities and beings are from the firſt being, and ſo far forth they are good.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>De Vera Relig.</hi> c. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Ipſum quantulumcunque eſſe bonum eſt</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auſtin</hi>) <hi>quiaſummum eſſe eſt ſummum bonum:</hi> the ſmalleſt being of all is good, becauſe the chiefeſt or greateſt being is the greateſt good. If M. <hi>P.</hi> will have any natural act <hi>(quà actus)</hi> not to proceed from the God of Nature, he will have a creature without a Creator.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Doth not Mr. <hi>P.</hi> by this Doctrine, juſtly contract on himſelf that guilt which he unjuſtly chargeth upon others, namely, of making God the Author of Sin? for if God be the Author of all natural actions (as hath been proved) and it be impoſſible (as he teacheth) to ſeparate the ſin from the action, then he that is the Author of the action, muſt needs be Author of the ſin alſo which is unſeparable from it. But I ſuppoſe he is not ſo dull-ſighted, but if he pleaſed he could eaſily diſcern a difference between the action and the evil quality of it. The roundneſs may be ſeparated from the Globe, and yet the matter of it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:37966:17"/>ſtill when it is put into another form. There are mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of actions wherein Natures work is the very ſame, whereof though ſome of them be evil, yet others of them may be without any evil at all.</p>
               <p>So far as Sin makes for the glory of God,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>4</label> ſo far he may both will and work it; for if he neither intends it, nor hath any hand at all in effecting it, how ſhall it make for his glory? there muſt be a cauſe that brings forth this effect, the ſinner himſelf intends it not, nor works to any ſuch end, but rather the contrary: therefore it muſt be the ſecret wiſdom and wonderful working of God that brings forth this effect; and how can he intend to have glory by ſuch or ſuch an action, and never intend the action it ſelf?</p>
               <p>If God onely permits,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>5</label> but neither intends nor hath any hand at all in the ſinful actions of men, then he is a meer ſpectator and idle beholder of all the actions of men in the world when ever they do evil. For if a man ſtands and ſees a thing to be done, which he neither wills to be done, nor not to be done, but leaves it to others to do as they pleaſe, without having any hand at all in it, neither help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nor hindring, is he nor an idle ſpectator? and if God carries himſelf in this ſort in regard of the ſinful actions of men, what ſhall become of his providence whereby he ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the world, ſince the greateſt number of actions done in the world are ſinful actions?</p>
               <p>Object. Mr. <hi>P.</hi> thinks to ſhift himſelf from this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by telling us,
<note place="margin">Cap. 3. Page 129.</note> 
                  <hi>That God doth wiſely order and diſpoſe of ſin after the committing of it, but doth not determine that it ſhall be done, or hath any hand in the doing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> But then ſtill it follows, that he ſtands as a meer ſpectator in regard of the greateſt part of actions that are done in the world; for all the while they are in acting he doth nothing at all about them, onely afterwards he or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders them to the beſt advantage. But how can this ſtand with the All-wiſe and All-working Providence of God (without which a ſparrow falls not to the ground) that he
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:37966:17"/>ſhould ſtand looking on whiles the greateſt part of actions are done in the world, and many of them of greateſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, and determine nor do any thing while they be done and paſt, onely afterwards imploy his wiſdom in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of them? For (to inſtance in ſome of our former examples) how can we think that when <hi>Joſeph</hi> was ſold in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Egypt,</hi> God had no hand in it, though his brethren did it out of envy and hatred againſt him, when he tells them that <hi>God ſent him before to preſerve them and their poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity alive, and to ſave them by a great deliverance;</hi> yea in them the whole Church of God which was included in <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobs</hi> family? yea why ſhould he repeat it again, ſaying, <hi>You ſent me not hither, but God ſent me,</hi> Gen. 45.7, 12. if God had not any hand at all in his ſending thither, yea, if he had not the chief hand? How can we think that God had no hand in <hi>Pharaohs</hi> oppreſſion of the Iſraelites, when he had determined it, and foretold it many years before, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.13, 16. or that he had no hand in his obſtinate refuſal to let them go (having received an expreſs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand from God to do it) when it is ſaid that <hi>the Lord hardned</hi> Pharaohs <hi>heart that he would not let them go,</hi> Exo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus 10.27. yea, that he <hi>raiſed him up for this purpoſe, that he might ſhew his power upon him?</hi> cap. 9.16. How can we think that the defection of the ten Tribes from the Houſe of <hi>David</hi> (which is called <hi>Rebellion,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 12.19.) was ſuch a thing as God had no hand in, when as he told <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboam</hi> by his prophet that he <hi>would rent the kingdom out of the hand of</hi> Solomon, <hi>and give ten Tribes of it to him?</hi> cap. 11.31. Can we think that God had no hand in the deſtruction of <hi>Samaria,</hi> and carrying away the ten Tribes by the king of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> when he calls the <hi>Aſſyrian his rod, and the ſtaff of his indignation,</hi> and that he <hi>would ſend him againſt an hypocritical nation, againſt the people of his wrath, and would give him a charge to take the ſpoil and prey; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit he did not mean ſo, neither did he think ſo</hi> (namely to do Gods work, but his own) but <hi>he thought to deſtroy and cut off nations not a few?</hi> Iſa. 10.6, 7. Can we think that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:37966:18"/>all the ſtrange changes and alterations that have been in Kingdoms and States, whereby the Government and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion hath been devolved from one hand to another (which ſeldom hath been done without much violence and wrong, yea without Treacheries, Murthers and Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed) were ſuch things wherein God had no hand, when it is ſaid that he doth theſe things, <hi>to the intent that men may know that the moſt High hath power over the Kingdoms of men, and giveth them to whom he will,</hi> Dan. 4.14. Can we think that the ſtrange commotions and ſhakings that of late have been amongſt our ſelves, whereby the whole frame of Government, both in Church and State, is changed from what it was, are ſuch things as God hath had no hand in? Certainly this were to make God a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry weak and impotent, or a very remiſs and careleſs Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor of the World, if he ſhould ſtand ſtill looking on while theſe things were in doing, and onely exerciſe his wiſdom, in ordering them afterwards.</p>
               <p>Object. But it is further objected, <hi>That God hates all ſin, and therefore can have no hand at all, either in willing or effecting of it: for no man will have any hand in doing what he hates.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Though he hates it, yet he permits it; (as is granted by all) and why doth he permit it, but becauſe he can get himſelf glory by it? and ſo far as it makes for his glory, he may both will it, and have ſome kinde of hand in working it: Though ſin be in it ſelf evil, yet it may have ſome reſpect of good, becauſe it may be made an occaſion of good. For the rule is true, <hi>Malum eſt in bono tanquam in ſubjecto,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Enchirid.</hi> cap. 96.</note> and <hi>actus peccati in genere entis bonus eſt, in genere moris malus.</hi> Hence <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Quamvis quae mala ſunt, in quantum mala ſunt, non ſunt bona, tamen ut non ſolum bona, ſed etiam mala ſint, bonum eſt.</hi> Although evil things be not good, ſo far as they are evil, yet it is good that not onely good things ſhould be, but evil things alſo.</p>
               <p>It is granted by all,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>6</label> that God puniſheth one ſin with
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:37966:18"/>another; as becauſe men received not the love of the truth, he gave them up to ſtrong deluſions, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.10. Now puniſhment is more then a bare permiſſion: It were ridiculous to ſay, that a Judge onely permitteth a Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor to be arraigned, condemned and executed.</p>
               <p>Thus I hope we have cleared the firſt thing propounded, namely, That Gods permiſſion is not ſuch an empty idle permiſſion, as is accompanied with no action nor operation at all. It follows now to ſhew, that though it be an operative permiſsion, yet he is not the Author of the evil permitted and committed; but when be works in the ſame action with wicked men, what they do wickedly and unjuſtly, he doth moſt holily, juſtly and righteouſly.</p>
               <p>That the truth of this may appear, it will be needful to look into the maner of Gods working in evil actions of men. This, though it be done in a wonderful and ineffa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble maner, yet ſo much may be diſcerned of it, as may ſerve to ſatisfie ſober mindes, and to clear God from all juſt imputation of any impurity or unholineſs.</p>
               <p>This in general may be ſufficient to clear him from all ſuch imputations, becauſe all thoſe things that proceed from him, whence evil minded men take any occaſion to be ſtirred up to evil, do in their own nature tend to good, and are occaſions of evil onely by accident, as the ſhining of the Sun may make weak eyes ſee worſe then before: So that he cannot be ſaid to be the Author of any evil, becauſe he is never <hi>cauſa per ſe,</hi> but onely <hi>per accidens,</hi> of any evil that falls out upon occaſion of any thing that he doth. All his diſpenſations towards man, do always in their own nature tend to good, and the evil that doth occaſionally reſult from them is <hi>praeter ſcopum operis,</hi> beſides the ſcope of the work that he doth. When a Phyſitian preſcribes to his Patient wholſome Phyſick, and ſuch as is in it ſelf fit for cure of his malady, and moſt proper for his diſeaſe; if this meets with ſome malignant humor in his body, whereby it occaſions greater ſickneſs, yea the death of the Patient, the Phyſitian cannot be
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:37966:19"/>ſaid to be the author of his ſickneſs or death, becauſe what he adminiſtred was to preſerve health and life, and that it wrought another effect, was onely by accident: So it is in this caſe betwixt God and ſinful men. The truth of this will more plainly appear, if we look into the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars. There are two ways eſpecially, whereby God may be ſaid to adminiſter occaſion of ſinning, and ſo to have ſome kinde of hand in it, namely, by his word, and by his works.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For the word of God, wicked men may ſometime take occaſion from that, to become more ſinful. The Apoſtle ſhews expreſly, that the Law of God hath an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacy in irritating and ſtirring the corruption of mans nature: For he ſaith, that <hi>ſin took occaſion by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and wrought in him all maner of concupiſcence,</hi> and <hi>ſin taking occaſion by the command, deceived him,</hi> Rom. 7.11. and that, <hi>when we were in the fleſh, the motions of ſin which were by the Law, did work in our members,</hi> Ver. 5. That the Law hath an efficacy in ſtirring up ſinful moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and in working in us all maner of concupiſcence, is plain by theſe expreſsons of the Apoſtle.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> If it be asked, how the Law of God, that is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, juſt and good, can be any occaſion of evil;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The anſwer is, That it ariſeth from the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety that is betwixt Gods holy Law, and mans corrupt heart. It is a true rule, that <hi>contraria juxta ſe poſita mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis eluceſcunt:</hi> when contraries are put together, their contrariety doth more appear. When fire and water are kept at a diſtance, the contrariety of their natures doth not much appear; but put them together, and then they fight one with another, till the ſtronger hath overcome the weaker. There is nothing more holy then the Law of God, being the perfect rule of all righteouſneſs and holineſs; there is nothing more corrupt then the heart of man, being the ſeat and ſink of all ſilthineſs and pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.19. Therefore the more cloſe this holy Law of God be applyed to the corrupt heart of man, the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:37966:19"/>more the innate corruption of it is irritated and ſtirred up. We ſee this in the example of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> the more ſtrongly the command was preſſed upon him, touching letting the Iſraelites go, the more ſtrongly did his rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious will riſe up againſt it: We may ſee this in the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary carriage of wicked men, let a proud profane ſwearer or filthy ſpeaker be rebuked for their ill language, the more they will exceed in this kinde: Look as when a ſtream is ſtopt, it riſeth higher, though no more water be added to it; ſo it is with thoſe who are wilfully wicked, when they are ſtopt in the courſe of their wickedneſs. Many other inſtances might be brought to make it appear, that the good word of God accidentally doth ſtir up the corruption that is in mens wicked hearts. When our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vior Chriſt preached to the Jews, the Phariſees were fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with wrath againſt him, <hi>Luke</hi> 4.28. When <hi>Stephen</hi> preached unto them, they gnaſhed their teeth againſt him, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.54. Chriſts Preaching and <hi>Stephens</hi> Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, had an efficiency in ſtirring up the anger and wrath of their hearers, they were accidental cauſes of it, but no faulty cauſes, they cannot be ſaid to be the Authors of their anger, though their Preaching occaſioned it. So it is when ever the good word of God doth ſtir up evil af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections in the hearts of wicked men, neither he nor his word are the Authors of that evil.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle ſaith, that <hi>The Law worketh wrath,</hi> Rom. 4.15. It worketh wrath no otherwiſe then it work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſin, namely, by accident; for it was the end and ſcope of the Law, to keep men from ſinning, and ſo to keep them from wrath: now as the Law works it, God works it, for the Law is Gods inſtrument; and as the Law cannot be ſaid to be the Author of ſin (though it doth accidentally ſtir corruption) no more can God be ſaid to be the Author of it.</p>
               <p>Yea, not onely the Law, but the Goſpel may be an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of increaſing mans ſin; for Chriſt tells the Jews, that <hi>if they had been blinde, they had had no ſin,</hi> but <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:37966:20"/>they ſaid they did ſee, therefore their ſin remained,</hi> John 9.41. and, <hi>This is the condemnation of the world, that light is come into the world, and men loved darkneſs more then light,</hi> John 3.19. So that the ſhining of the light of the Goſpel, may occaſion an increaſe both of men; ſin and condemnation, and yet be no faulty caſe of it: In this ſenſe alſo Chriſt ſaith of himſelf, that <hi>he came not to ſend peace, but the ſword;</hi> that <hi>he came to ſet a man at variacne againſt his father, and the daughter againſt the mother,</hi> Mat. 10.34, 35. that <hi>he came to ſet fire on the earth,</hi> Luke 12.49. Will Mr. <hi>P.</hi> tell us here, that Chriſt came onely to ſuffer thoſe fiery perſecutions that were ſtirred up in the world by the Preaching of the Goſpel, or thoſe enmities that were ſtirred up betwixt neareſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, upon occaſion of it; or that Chriſt was the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of theſe perſecutions and enmities, and of thoſe ſtirs and troubles that were raiſed up in the world, when he cauſed his Kingdom to be ſet up; or that the Apoſtles were the Authors of thoſe diviſions and tumults which were ſtirred up at <hi>Epheſus</hi> and other places, by occaſion of their Preaching, <hi>Acts</hi> 19.23. and that they were tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly charged by their adverſaries, to be <hi>ſubverters of the ſtate of the world?</hi> Acts 17.6. yet upon the very like ground doth he charge many Orthodox Divines to make God to be the Author of ſin, becauſe they teach that he hath ſome kinde of efficiency in it, by adminiſtring occaſions, as the Preaching of the Apoſtles was the occaſion of theſe tumults, when as all the occaſions that he adminiſters tend to good, as the Apoſtles Preaching did.</p>
               <p n="2">2. God may be ſaid ſometimes to adminiſter occaſions of ſinning by his works: As 1. by his works of mercy, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſentence againſt an evil work is not ſpeedily executed, therefore the hearts of the ſons of men are fully ſet to do evil,</hi> Eccleſ. 8.11. <hi>Theſe things thou haſt done and I was ſilent, and thou thoughteſt that I was ſuch an one as thy ſelf,</hi> Pſal. 50.21. <hi>When</hi> Jeſhurun <hi>waxed fat, he kicked the heel,</hi> Deut. 32.15. The bountifulneſs, goodneſs and long-ſuffering of God do
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:37966:20"/>in their own nature lead to repentance, yet here they are made occaſions of ſinning.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As the works of his mercy, ſo of his juſtice, are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times made occaſions of ſinning. When God led his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple through the wilderneſs, he ſuffered them ſometimes to want water, otherwhile to want fleſh for their food: and this was <hi>to humble them and prove them, that he might do them good in their latter end,</hi> Deut. 8.2. But the bad ones amongſt them hence took occaſion to murmure and to open their mouthes againſt God. When the Lord pours out the vials of his wrath upon the followers of the beaſt, hence they take occaſion to <hi>blaſpheme the God of heaven for their pains and ſores, and repented not of their works,</hi> Rev. 16.9, 11.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The works of Gods Providence are ſometimes alſo made occaſions of ſinning: it was the work of Gods pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and providence that made the Iſraelites multiply ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly in <hi>Egypt,</hi> which ſhould have made <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſo much more to reſpect them, yet hence he takes occaſion to oppreſs them. It was a work of providence that brought <hi>David</hi> to <hi>Ahimelech</hi> the prieſt for relief in his flight, at ſuch a time as <hi>Doeg</hi> the Edomite was there: this might have ſtirred him up to ſuccour, at leaſt to pity <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> in his diſtreſs, but hence he took occaſion by his falſe ſlanders, to ſtir up <hi>Saul</hi> to murther all the Lords Prieſts at <hi>Nob,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.18. It was a work of providence that brought the wiſe men to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to enquire after the king of the Jews that was then born, yet hence <hi>Herod</hi> takes occaſion to ſeek to kill Chriſt, and rather then fail, to kill all the male-children that were in <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> and in the region round about, that were two years old and under, <hi>Mat.</hi> 2.16.</p>
               <p>Thus we ſee that God by the works both of his Mercy, Juſtice and Providence, may adminiſter occaſions of evil to evil minded men, now ſhall we ſay that he is therefore the Author of the evil which they do, when all theſe oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions are ſuch things as do in their own nature tend to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:37966:21"/>good, and by accident onely are made occaſion of evil.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>But how is it poſsible that God and man ſhould work together in the ſame action, and the one be blame-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and the other blameleſs?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe they differ both in the ground, maner, and end of their working. 1. They differ in the ground: the ground of Gods working is the counſel of his own will, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.11. which is always moſt holy and juſt: the ground of wicked mens actions is the motion of their own wicked wills, they ſeek to fulfil the will of the fleſh and of their mindes, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.3. in their evil actions they do that which is contrary to the revealed will of God (and his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret will they know not) if they do the ſame things that God wills, yet not becauſe he wills them, but upon ſome other grounds. When <hi>Joſephs</hi> brethren ſold him into <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> they did it out of envy againſt him, but God did it out of love to him and his father <hi>Jacob,</hi> and his whole family.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The differ in the maner of their working; for in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful actions God works with wicked men not as a moral cauſe, but a natural cauſe onely: he doth no where com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, counſel or perſwade men to do evil, but altogether the contrary; and when they do evil, they are carried on by the dictate of their depraved judgements, and ſway of their own corrupt wills and diſordered affections. God being the Author of Nature, it belongs to him to uphold the creature in all its natural motions and actions; and he moves the creatures with a motion agreeable to their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral natures, both irrational and rational creatures. When he moves good men that are guided by his Spirit, they work according to their natures, when he moves bad men, they alſo work according to their natures, and this without any iniquity or injuſtice in God; for of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural motion he is the Author and proper Cauſe, of the obliquity of it, he is onely an accidental cauſe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not the Author.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They differ in the end; for the end of all Gods actions
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:37966:21"/>is himſelf and his own glory, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.4. but wicked men aim at themſelves, at their own glory, or ſome other baſe reſpect of their own. Is not this <hi>great Babel which I have built for the honor of my Majeſty?</hi> (ſaith that proud King, <hi>Dun.</hi> 4.27.) When the High Prieſts and Elders de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered up Chriſt to be crucified, they did it out of envy and hatred againſt him, to the end they might be rid of him; but God did it out of love, that by this means all his elect might come to be ſaved out of their loſt condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Object. 2. A ſecond principal Objection brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Gods abſolute Decree, is, <hi>That it infers a neceſſity of ſinning, and ſo frees man from all blame in all his ſinful actions, becauſe what God hath decreed muſt neceſſarily come to paſs.</hi> This Mr. <hi>P.</hi> often urgeth,
<note place="margin">Cap. 1. pag. 13.</note> touching at it almoſt in every other page, and making us to ſay that men ſhall ſin of neceſſity, do what they can to the contrary.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. If Mr. <hi>P.</hi> had pleaſed to ſtoop ſo low as to take notice of that diſtinction uſually given by our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines betwixt <hi>neceſſitas abſoluta &amp; hypothetica,</hi> or (which is the ſame) <hi>neceſſitas conſequentis vel cauſae, &amp; neceſsitas conſequentiae,</hi> he might have been convinced of the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of this Objection, and of the falſeneſs of that impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation which thereby he ſeeks to faſten on us.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It hath been already proved to him, that Gods De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree doth no whit infringe the liberty of mans will, or take away the contingency of the ſecond cauſes; to which he hath given no anſwer.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If he hath forgotten, or will take no notice of what was ſpoken of this ſubject, in the Obſervations which Mr. <hi>Barly</hi> prefixed before his Book, the ſame things ſhall be told him again with ſome addition.</p>
               <p>That the Will and Decree of God doth not violate the liberty of mans will, may appear upon theſe following grounds:</p>
               <p>Chriſts death was decreed,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>1</label> for he <hi>was delivered by the determinate counſel of God,</hi> Acts 2.23. yet he died moſt
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:37966:22"/>freely, for he ſaith that <hi>he laid down his life, when no man had power to take it from him,</hi> John 10.17, 18. Beſides, if Chriſts death had not been voluntary, it had not been meritorious; if it had not been an act of moſt free and perfect obedience, it could have merited no reward at the hands of God, either for himſelf or us.</p>
               <p>The firm ſtanding of the good Angels is a free act,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>2</label> they are not enforced to it, yet this was decreed, for they are called <hi>Elect Angels,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.21. The obedience and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice which the Saints perform in heaven, they perform moſt freely and willingly without any conſtraint or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity (hence we are taught to pray that <hi>the will of God may be done on earth as it is done in heaven</hi>) and when the Saints on earth repent, believe and obey, they do it freely, they are not carried to it by any natural or violent neceſſity, yet all theſe things are decreed; for it is ſaid, <hi>he hath cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen us before the foundation of the world, to be holy and without blame before him in love,</hi> Eph. 1.4. And that God hath from the beginning <hi>choſen us to ſalvation through the ſanctification of the Spirit, and the belief of the truth,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2.13.</p>
               <p>In all our natural motions and actions,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>3</label> in our eating and drinking, ſitting, walking, diſcourſing, talking, we act freely: ſo alſo in our civil affairs, in our journeying, buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſelling, and all other buſineſſes belonging to our ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Callings, we act freely without any compulſion or neceſſity: this I ſuppoſe Mr. <hi>P.</hi> will not deny, and will he deny that theſe things are appointed and determined by God? What a kinde of Governor of the world will he make him to be, when the greateſt part of things that are done in the world, all the actions of men and angels, and all contingent events what ever, are excluded from the compaſs of his Decree? How doth this agree with Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture-Doctrine, which teacheth that <hi>mans goings are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered of the Lord,</hi> Prov. 20.24. That <hi>the way of man is not in himſelf,</hi> Jer. 10.23. yea, <hi>that in him we live, move, and have our being,</hi> Acts 17. in all our natural motions and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:37966:22"/>actions what we do, he doth, and what he doth in time, he hath determined before all time, otherwiſe he ſhould not work by counſel.</p>
               <p>Gods Decree is <hi>actus ad intra,</hi> an act within himſelf;
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>4</label> and of thoſe kinde of actions the rule holds true, that they do <hi>nihil ponere in objecto:</hi> Gods Decree alone never works any thing upon the creature, till it comes to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, till he puts forth his inward purpoſe by ſome out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward action: Unleſs therefore it can be ſhown how God by ſome outward action upon man, doth neceſſitate mans will, his inward purpoſe and decree alone will never do it. And we finde by dayly experience, that we ſin as freely as we eat or drink, or do any other thing in the world: Beſides, Gods inward purpoſe and decree is altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to a ſinner, and <hi>ignoti nulla cupido;</hi> therefore this can never move him to any ſinful act.</p>
               <p>The Decree of God is ſo far from neceſſitating mans will, and infringing the liberty of the ſecond cauſes,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>5</label> as it is the ground and foundation of all freedom and liberty: for he doth not onely <hi>decernere rem ipſam, ſed modum rei,</hi> he doth not onely determine the thing it ſelf that ſhall be done, but the maner how it ſhall be done; for the <hi>modi rerum,</hi> are not really diſtinguiſhed from the things them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but ſo nearly conjoyned, as they cannot be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered; as therefore ſome things come to paſs neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe God hath decreed they ſhall come to paſs ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily, ſo other things come to paſs contingently, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath decreed they ſhall come to paſs contingent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; for he hath decreed that all things ſhall come to paſs, either neceſſarily or contingently, and the effect of his decree muſt be as certain in the one as the other.</p>
               <p>Neceſſity and contingency ariſe from the intrinſecal na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the things, and not from any thing extrinſecal.
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>6</label> In things that come to paſs neceſſarily, there is ſuch a near and ſtrong connexion betwixt the cauſe and the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, that if the cauſe go before, the effect muſt needs follow after; as if fire be fire, it muſt needs have the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:37966:23"/>property of burning, if a ſtone be a ſtone, it muſt needs have the property of deſcending; but in contingent ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, though the thing ſhall certainly come to paſs, (up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuppoſal of Gods Decree) yet there is no ſuch neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary connexion betwixt the cauſe and effect; but in regard of the nature of the things, they might have been other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then they are. It is ſaid, <hi>The Lord holds the winds in his fiſt,</hi> Prov. 30.4. therefore the motion of them is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his appointment; when he cauſed a ſtrong Eaſt winde to blow upon the head of <hi>Jonah, Jon.</hi> 4.8. this was according to his appointment and decree, yet this was not out of any natural neceſſity planted in the winde, for that was equally diſpoſed to have blown out of the Weſt or any other quarter, if it pleaſed God ſo to order it, for <hi>the winde bloweth where it liſteth,</hi> John 3.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>But if things may come to paſs otherwiſe then they do, then Gods Decrees may be fruſtrated.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It follows not, becauſe (as before was ſhewed) he hath decreed that they ſhall come to paſs in the ſame maner that they do, namely, that neceſſary things ſhall come to paſs neceſſarily, and contingent things contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently; and his Decree can no more be fruſtrated in the one then in the other: For though it be neceſſary that what God hath decreed ſhould come to paſs, yet it is not neceſſary it ſhould come to paſs, <hi>neceſſario modo &amp; neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſariis mediis;</hi> God had decreed that Chriſts bones ſhould not be broken, therefore it was neceſſary this ſhould take effect, yet the Soldiers were not hindred by any ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsity from doing it, but did as freely abſtain from breaking them, as they did freely break the Thieves bones. God had decreed the birthright and bleſsing to <hi>Jacob,</hi> yet this came to paſs by as contingent means as might be; for there was no neceſsity that <hi>Eſau</hi> ſhould come hungry from hunting, that <hi>Jacob</hi> ſhould have his pottage in a readineſs, that he ſhould propound them as a price for the birthright, that <hi>Eſau</hi> ſhould accept of the bargain, that <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſhould miſtake <hi>Jacob</hi> for <hi>Eſau,</hi> and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:37966:23"/>his ſavory meat for <hi>Eſaus</hi> Veniſon; there was no neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity in any of theſe things, but all was done moſt freely, yet all was guided by a ſecret and certain providence, ſo as the event ſhould not fail to come to paſs as God had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined. Every neceſſary truth is an eternal truth, for it is a true rule, <hi>Quod neceſſarium eſt ſemper verum eſt, nec falſum eſſe poteſt,</hi> A neceſſary propoſition is that which is alway true, and can never be falſe: That <hi>Cain</hi> ſhould kill his brother, was no neceſſary truth before the thing was done; that man ſhould be a reaſonable creature, was a neceſſary truth before man was created: It was no neceſſary truth that <hi>Adam</hi> ſhould eat the forbidden fruit, before he had eaten it; and though then it was a truth, yet no neceſſary truth: for no circumſtance can change the nature of things, ſo as to make a neceſſary truth to become contingent, or a contingent truth to become ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary. True it is, that when a thing is done, it cannot be undone, (for a thing cannot be and not be both at one time) but it was not neceſſary it ſhould be done, if it be a thing of a contingent nature. What I now ſpeak or write, is neceſſary ſhould be thus ſpoken or written; but before it was not neceſſary I ſhould ſpeak or write any thing, theſe being acts of liberty and freedom; ſo it is in all actions of like nature, in all contingent actions. This for the ſecond Objection.</p>
               <p>Object. 3. A third thing objected againſt the Abſolute Decree, is, <hi>That it is againſt Gods Juſtice; for if the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of Reprobation go before the foreſight of ſin, then the innocent creature is deſigned to deſtruction; which cannot agree with the Juſtice of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> For anſwer of this, Two things are needful to be proved; 1. That it is no injuſtice in God to puniſh the innocent creature. 2. That by the Decree of Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, no innocent creature is deſigned to deſtruction. For the firſt, it may be proved theſe ways:
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>1</label>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>P.</hi> aſſerts Infants to be innocent creatures,
<note place="margin">Cap. 4. Page 25.</note> becauſe they never did hurt any man in thought, word or deed;
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:37966:24"/>and theſe are ſubject to death, and he cannot deny death to be a puniſhment, for it is the wages of ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23. And though death differs in degree from damnation, yet it is a puniſhment, and God cannot be unjuſt in any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree. It may be Mr. <hi>P.</hi> may finde out ſome anſwer to this; therefore we add further,</p>
               <p>Chriſt Jeſus was the moſt innocent perſon that ever was in the world,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>2</label> one that <hi>knew no ſin, neither was any guile found in his mouth,</hi> one <hi>that fulfilled all righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</hi> one <hi>in whom the Father was well pleaſed,</hi> for <hi>he had done all his pleaſure;</hi> yet <hi>he laid on him the iniquities of us all, he was wounded for our iniquities, and broken for our tranſgreſſions,</hi> Iſa. 53. <hi>The juſt ſuffered for the unjuſt,</hi> 1 Pet. 3.18. Yea he ſuffered ſuch a meaſure of his Fathers wrath, as was anſwerable to that, which all thoſe who are ſaved by him, ſhould have ſuffered in hell; for he being their ſurety, it was neceſſary that he ſhould fully diſcharge their debt, by making full ſatisfaction, in paying that which they ſhould have paid.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>P.</hi> knows well that many innocent creatures dayly ſuffer for his ſake,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>3</label> and are put to divers kindes of deaths, ſome have their throats cut, ſome are ſtrangled, ſome are knockt on the head, according to the will and pleaſure of thoſe by whom they are killed; and theſe are ſuch as never offended or deſerved any ill at his hands: and may not God uſe the ſame liberty with creatures of his own making, as man doth with thoſe creatures which he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver made? He would think it ridiculous if any ſhould cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor againſt him for cruelty and injuſtice, when he treads a worm under his foot, or cruſheth a fly ſitting on the wall; yet there is not ſo great a diſproportion betwixt him and the ſmalleſt worm, as there is betwixt him (or the greateſt King in the world) and the great Creator. Man compared with God, being but as <hi>a drop that hangs on a bucket,</hi> or <hi>as the duſt that cleaves to the ballance,</hi> which ſwayes it neither one way nor another,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>4</label> 
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.15.</p>
               <p>May not the Potter do what he will with the veſſel
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:37966:24"/>which he hath made without any imputation of injuſtice, yea though he breaks it in pieces, or puts it to the baſeſt uſes? the Apoſtle makes Gods power over his Creature, to be full as large as the Potter hath over the Veſſel that he hath made, and gives this anſwer to the like Objection, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.21. God was not bound to preſerve man in his being after he was made, for he might have annihilated him as he made us of nothing, ſo he might bring us to nothing: and ſome deaths are leſs then annihilation. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was he bound to preſerve man from a ſinful being, as he did ſome of the Angels, but he might ſuffer him to fall, as he did ſome of them, and then deal with him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly. Thus we ſee it is no injuſtice in God to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict ſufferings upon innocent creatures.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That by the Decree of Reprobation, innocent creatures are not deſigned to deſtruction, appears,</p>
               <p>Becauſe Reprobation is that everlaſting purpoſe of God,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>1</label> whereby he hath decreed to glorifie his juſtice in the juſt condemnation of ſinful men: here ſin goes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore condemnation, though it goes not before Gods De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree: for condemnation is the execution, and is in time, whereas the Decree is before all time. It is a true rule, that <hi>Deus vult hoc eſſe propter hoc, ſed non vult hoc propter hoc,</hi> the one hath reference to the execution, the other to the decree: though there be a cauſe of the being of a thing, yet there is none of Gods will. It is the Tenet of the Schoolmen, <hi>Nullamdari poſſe cauſam decreti di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vini ex parte volentis, ſed tantùm ex parte volitorum.</hi> There can be no cauſe given of the Will and Decree of God, as it is his act, but onely of the things willed by him, none of the Decree, but onely of the Execution. Mr. <hi>P.</hi> ſeems ſometimes to grant this, and if he would ſtand to it, the controverſie might ſoon be at an end, for nothing is needful to go before the effect, but the cauſe, that which hath efficiency in ſome kinde or other in producing it; and if there can be no kinde of cauſe going before Gods Decree, his Decree may be without it.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:37966:25"/>
               <p>God doth condemn no man in time but for ſin;
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>2</label> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he determined to condemn no man but for ſin, for he doth things in time, in that maner and order that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to do them before all time. He actually con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns no man but for ſin actually exiſting, till after men have ſinned, but ſin exiſts in time; therefore if he ſhould determine nothing touching mans everlaſting eſtate, till after he hath ſinned, his Decrees ſhould not be eternal but temporary: and ſo it is in effect according to this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which teacheth, That there is no abſolute nor pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptory Decree paſſed upon men, but upon foreſight of what they will do. And as for the Conditional Decree it is as good as none; becauſe (as hath been ſhewed) it is equally diſpoſed to mens damnation, as well as their ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
               <p>Though ſin doth not go before Gods Decree,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>3</label> yet nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is his Decree without the conſideration of ſin, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he decrees all things <hi>ſimul &amp; ſemel, uno actu ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſsimo,</hi> (as hath been ſhewed) there is no <hi>prius &amp; poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> in him or in his Decrees; but becauſe we are not able with one ſimple act to apprehend the ſeveral things which God hath decreed touching mans everlaſting eſtate, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Divines uſually place an order in his Decrees, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in one thing goes before another (though not in him, yet in our conſideration) yet this is ſuch an order as agrees with the order of nature, wherein the cauſe always goes before the effect, and the end before the means: and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this ground the foreſight of ſin cannot go before Gods Decree, becauſe when he decrees to permit ſin (without which there can be no foreſight of it) the end of this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion muſt needs be the manifeſtation of his glory in the merciful Salvation of ſome, and juſt Condemnation of others; therefore this muſt be firſt decreed according to the order of nature, though for time all be done at one inſtant. Beſides, when God decreed to create man, the end which he propounded to himſelf in this work, was his own glory, and that not onely in general, but in that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:37966:25"/>way, in that particular ſtate and condition of man whence in the end he receives his glory: but at laſt he receives greateſt glory in the Salvation of ſome, and Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of others; therefore this was the end which he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, when he intended mans creation: for to ſay that he intended no certain end in this great work, or was fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate of his intentions, is altogether unbeſeeming the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent nature of God. But Mr. <hi>P.</hi> thus undertakes to prove that reprobation follows the foreſight of ſin.</p>
               <p>Object.
<note place="margin">Cap. 4. page 5.</note> 
                  <hi>We grant</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that Damnation follows the foreſight of ſin, but Damnation alway follows Reprobation;</hi> ergo, <hi>Reprobation follows the foreſight of ſin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He much triumphs in this Objection, telling us we put a bitter jeer upon the greateſt part of mankinde, to ſay they are rejected without reſpect of ſin, and yet not dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned without reſpect of ſin, this following the other.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here we may tell Mr. <hi>P.</hi> that he puts his pitiful Sophiſtry upon his Readers, this Argument being a meer Fallacy; for here the concluſion is general, whereas in the third figure (as this Argument is) it alway ought to be particular, the deceitfulneſs of it will appear in the like inſtance: Suppoſe a man intends to build a houſe fit for his habitation; by this kinde of Logick we may thus argue:
<list>
                     <item>The building of the houſe follows after the providing Wood, Stone, and other materials:</item>
                     <item>But the building of the houſe follows after his intention to build it;</item>
                     <item>Therefore his intention to build his houſe, follows after the providing of Wood, and Stone, and other fit materials.</item>
                     <item>This is Mr. <hi>P.</hi> his <hi>acumen</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Object. But Mr. <hi>P.</hi> objects,
<note place="margin">Cap. 3. Page 66.</note> 
                  <hi>That it is impoſsible</hi> (as implying a contradiction) <hi>that God ſhould decree to repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate any without intuition of ſin, and yet at the ſame time to decree not to damn without reſpect of ſin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. It is very poſsible that Reprobation ſhould
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:37966:26"/>be without foreſight of ſin, and yet Damnation not to be ſo, becauſe theſe differ both in nature and time; repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation being an immanent act terminated in himſelf, dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation being a tranſient act, terminated in man; repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation being from all eternity, damnation being in time; the one is the Decree, the other the Execution. To de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree to damn, is to decree to do a thing in time. We may as well ſay that a man is ſaved as ſoon as he is elected, as damned ſo ſoon as he is reprobated.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is very improper to ſay that God doth decree to reprobate, as if he ſhould decree to decree; whereas re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation it ſelf is the decree: but it is uſual with Mr. <hi>P.</hi> to confound the Decree with the Execution, and ſo to jumble theſe together as thereby a miſt is caſt upon the eyes of the Reader, that he ſhall not diſcern the truth.</p>
               <p>Object. 4. A fourth Objection againſt the Abſolute Decree, is, <hi>That it cannot ſtand with Gods Philanthropy, with his love to mankinde;</hi> for Mr. <hi>P.</hi> tells us, <hi>That he hates nothing which he hath made:</hi> and the Scripture tells us, <hi>That he is gracious, merciful, abundant in goodneſs and truth, that his mercy is over all his works, and therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns none to be deſtroyed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Mr. <hi>P.</hi> tells us indeed that God hates no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that he hath made, but the Scripture tells us no ſuch thing, but rather the quite contrary; for it ſaith, That the Lord <hi>loved</hi> Jacob, <hi>and hated</hi> Eſau, <hi>and that before they were born.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Object. To this Mr. <hi>P.</hi> replies, <hi>That this hatred is to be underſtood onely in regard of temporal bleſsings, of the inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance of the land of</hi> Canaan.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This evaſion hath been ſufficiently confuted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, in confirmation of the ſeventh Argument againſt the Conditional Decree, where was ſhewed 1. that the hatred here ſpoken of ſtands directly in oppoſition to the love wherewith <hi>Jacob</hi> was loved; but that was the love of Election, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.11. compared with <hi>verſe</hi> 13.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The earthly <hi>Canaan</hi> was a type of the heavenly, why
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:37966:26"/>elſe had <hi>Eſau</hi> the black Character of Profaneneſs ſtampt on him, for paſſing away his right to it, by ſo ſlightly ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling his birth-right? <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.16.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In regard of outward bleſſings <hi>Eſau</hi> was no whit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior to <hi>Jacob,</hi> but rather above him; for he had the fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the earth, the pleaſant mount <hi>Seir</hi> for his poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, whereas <hi>Jacob</hi> was a ſtranger in the land of <hi>Canaan, Pſal.</hi> 105.12. having no poſſeſſion there, but onely the burying-place which <hi>Abraham</hi> had bought, <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.15. therefore it is ſaid, That <hi>God gave</hi> Abraham <hi>no inherit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in the land, no not ſo much as whereon to ſet his foot,</hi> Acts 7.5.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Eſau</hi> had abundance of all things, and therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed his brothers preſents, telling him <hi>he had enough.</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo he was a man of great place, for he came to meet his brother attended with four hundred men, ſo that <hi>Jacob</hi> bowed down to the ground before him, and called him his lord, <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.18. and 33.3. ſo that he was no whit inferior to his brother in regard of outward bleſſings.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. Secondly, for thoſe Scriptures which hold forth God to be ſo merciful, gracious, good to all, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It is granted that there is a common bounty and goodneſs which God extendeth to all mankinde, making the <hi>Sun to ſhine, and rain to fall upon the juſt and unjuſt,</hi> Matth. 5.45. but his ſpecial Grace and Mercy he extends onely to thoſe who are the proper objects of it, namely, thoſe whom he hath choſen to be veſſels of Mercy. Why may not God have his Favorites as well as Kings have theirs? Hence it is ſaid, that <hi>he will be gracious to whom he will be gracious,</hi> Exod. 33.19. which argues that he will not be gracious alike, and there are ſome ſpoken of in Scripture who <hi>were made to be taken and deſtroyed,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.12. <hi>who before of old were ordained to condemnation,</hi> Jude 4. therefore all are not alike objects of mercy. And herein appears the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of free Grace and ſpecial Mercy, namely, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the peculiarity of it; it is as rare as precious: it were no great priviledge to be Favorite of a Prince, if
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:37966:27"/>all Subjects were favored alike, or none were favored, but according to their deſerts; therefore ſpecial Grace is not confuſedly ſcattered amongſt all by a general offer, take it who will, but confined to a few: hence Chriſts people are called <hi>a peculiar people,</hi> Titus 2.14. and his flock is ſaid to be <hi>a little flock,</hi> Luke 12.32. and <hi>though the number of</hi> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael <hi>be as the ſand of the ſea, yet a remnant onely ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,</hi> for the <hi>Lord will finiſh his work, and cut it ſhort in righteouſneſs,</hi> Rom. 9.27, 28.</p>
               <p>Object.
<note place="margin">Cap. 3. page 83.</note> But for ſpecial Grace Mr. <hi>P.</hi> tells us, <hi>It is ſo called becauſe it ſerves</hi> ad ſpeciales habitus &amp; actus, <hi>to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry habit, or act, or thought of good that is done by man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is ſuch a notion of ſpecial Grace as I think but few have been acquainted with: but let him tells us whether theſe ſpecial acts and habits be effects of that ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Grace which is given to ſome onely, to ſuch whom God loves with a ſpecial and peculiar love, or imparted to all men indifferently: If the former, then it is called ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial, in reference to ſome ſpecial perſons to whom it is communicated, and thoſe ſpecial effects which it produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth in theſe more then in others. If the latter (which Mr. <hi>P.</hi> ſeems to intend) what a choice and ſpecial Grace hath he found out for us, which is beſtowed as largely upon <hi>Judas</hi> as upon <hi>Peter,</hi> upon the damned in hell, as thoſe who are ſaved in heaven? When <hi>Judas</hi> preached and caſt out devils, he did it by a Grace that ſerved for thoſe ſpecial acts and habits whereby he was enabled to do theſe things. When others called Chriſt Lord, Lord, yea not onely made an outward profeſſion of him, but propheſied and caſt out devils in his name, they did it by vertue of a Grace that ſerved for theſe ſpecial acts and habits, yet Chriſt will ſay to them at the great Day, <hi>I know you not, depart from me ye workers of iniquity,</hi> Matth 7.22. What comfort can a man take in ſuch a ſpecial Grace, as he may carry with him to hell? Doth not Scripture-language found in another kinde of ſtrain then this? as when our Savior gives thanks to his Father, that <hi>he had hid the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:37966:27"/>of his kingdom from the wiſe and prudent, and reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them to babes,</hi> Matth. 11.25. and tells his Diſciples, that <hi>it was given to them to know the myſteries of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of heaven, and not to others,</hi> cap. 13.11. and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>Not many Wiſe, not many mighty, not many noble whom God hath called,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.26. and ſaith of himſelf, that when he was a blaſphemer and a perſecuter, yet he <hi>found mercy, and the grace of the Lord was exceedingly abundant towards him,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.13, 14.</p>
               <p>Object. 5. A fifth Objection (which makes a great noiſe) is, <hi>That this Doctrine cannot ſtand with the truth of God; for he hath ſaid, He hath no pleaſure in the death of wicked men, and confirms this with an oath,</hi> Ezek. 33.11. <hi>and ſaith expreſly, That he would not that any ſhould periſh,</hi> 2 Pet. 3.9.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. For that place of <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> the anſwer is by diſtinguiſhing of that which is called in Scripture by the name of the will of God. It ſignifies either his ſecret will, or his revealed will; the will of his purpoſe, or the will of his precept and command; this place is not to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of the will of his purpoſe (which onely is properly his will) but of the will of his precept or command, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he enjoyns men to do thoſe things that tend to life, and to decline all thoſe things that tend to death, and therefore may be ſaid not to will their death: eſpecially all his outward diſpenſations towards men, tending to the ſame end with his command, namely, to procure life, not death.</p>
               <p>Object. Againſt this Mr. <hi>P.</hi> replies, <hi>That the revealed will of God, or the will of his command, is</hi> propriè voluntas, <hi>properly the will of God; for the whole word of God revealed in Scripture, is properly his will.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> For anſwer of this, two things are needful to be proved; Firſt, That the revealed will of God or his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, is not properly his will. Secondly, That all thoſe whom God wills to be ſaved, <hi>voluntate propriè dicta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> with the will of his purpoſe, with his internal will, are, or ſhall be certainly ſaved.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:37966:28"/>
               <p n="1">1. For the firſt, when two things are attributed to God that are contrary one to the other, both of them cannot poſſibly be taken properly; as when it is ſaid, that <hi>it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented the Lord that he made</hi> Saul <hi>king,</hi> 1 Sam. 15.11. and, that <hi>the Strength of Iſrael cannot lie nor repent,</hi> verſe 29. Both theſe cannot be taken properly (for then there would be a contradiction) that onely therefore is to be taken properly which agrees to the nature of God; he is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable, and therefore cannot repent; the other is to be taken figuratively, he is ſaid to repent, becauſe he doth the ſame thing that a repenting man, he changeth his action as a repenting man doth: he never changeth his minde. So when it is ſaid, that God wills not the death of a ſinner, and that he hardens whom he will, and makes ſome veſſels to diſhonor, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.18.21. Both theſe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be taken properly, therefore that muſt be taken pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly which agrees with the nature of God, and the other to be taken figuratively: now it properly agrees to the nature of God that his will ſhould be accompliſhed (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is Omnipotent) therefore when he is ſaid not to will the death of a ſinner, and yet many ſinners die ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingly; this cannot be underſtood of his will properly taken, namely, the will of his Purpoſe and Decree, but of the will of his precept and command, and of his outward diſpenſations towards men, all which in themſelves tend to the preſerving from death.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſame name cannot be properly given to two things whoſe nature doth really differ: as for inſtance, when Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Let the dead bury the dead;</hi> this cannot be properly taken in both places, becauſe in the firſt it is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of thoſe who are ſpiritually dead, in the other of thoſe who are naturally dead.</p>
               <p>Now that the will of Gods purpoſe, or his internal will, and the will of his precept and command do really differ in their own nature, is thus proved:</p>
               <p n="1">1. The will of Gods purpoſe, or his internal will, is eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, all his Decrees are from everlaſting, but his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:37966:28"/>are given forth in time; the commands belonging both to the moral and ceremonial Law, were not given out till the world was above two thouſand years old; and the word of the Lord came to the Prophets at ſeveral times; yea, there was a time when there was no Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures or written word of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Will of Gods purpoſe is immutable and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable, The counſels of the Lord ſtand for ever, and his thoughts to all generations, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.11. but his commands are mutable, as we ſee in the example of <hi>Abraham,</hi> who received a command to kill his ſon, which afterwards was reverſed, and in all the precepts of the ceremonial Law.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The will of his purpoſe cannot be reſiſted: <hi>Who hath reſiſted his will?</hi> Rom. 9. The will of his precept is dayly reſiſted by wicked men, and too often by his beſt ſervants.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The will of his purpoſe is alway fulfilled, he doth whatſoever he will: but the will of his command is not ſo; <hi>This is the will of God, even your ſanctification,</hi> 1 Theſ. 4.3. yet all men are not ſanctified.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The will of his purpoſe is an act within himſelf, and therefore not really differing from himſelf, the will of his command is ſomething proceeding from himſelf; ſo that theſe do as really differ as the Creator and the Creature, the one being eternal, immutable and irreſiſtible, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther temporary, mutable, reſiſtible. The command in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed by a Metonymy, is called the will of God (becauſe ſometimes, not always, it ſhews what the will of his purpoſe is) yet it is not, nor cannot be properly his will, upon the grounds before named; neither doth it follow hence, that there are two wills in God, but onely that there are two things that are ſet forth by one and the ſame name, which is very uſual in Scripture. Neither doth it follow, that one Will of God is contrary to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, for <hi>contraria</hi> muſt be <hi>ad idem;</hi> but theſe are not the ſame, but do really differ, as hath been already pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:37966:29"/>True it is, that God doth properly will to give forth ſuch and ſuch commands, but his will and purpoſe is one thing, and his command another, really differing from it. Thus much to ſhew that Gods revealed will, his precepts and commands are not properly his will.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For the ſecond thing, namely, That all thoſe to whom God wills ſalvation, <hi>voluntate propriè dicta,</hi> with the will of his purpoſe and decree, ſhall moſt certainly be ſaved, needs no great proof; for this will of his being an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable, irreſiſtible, omnipotent will, it muſt needs take effect. <hi>Our God is in heaven, and doth whatſoever he will,</hi> Pſal. 115.3. <hi>Whatſoever pleaſed the Lord, that did he, both in heaven and in earth,</hi> Pſal. 135.6. There are two principles onely needful for producing any effect, <hi>poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia &amp; voluntas,</hi> and where theſe concur, the effect muſt needs follow: If God doth really and internally will and deſire the ſalvation of men, what ſhould hinder the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting it, ſince his power is anſwerable to his will? If mens power were anſwerable to their will, they would do any thing that they have a minde to.</p>
               <p>If it be ſaid that he wills it conditionally, 1. This con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional will hath been already refuted, and it hath been ſhewed, that conditions belong not to Gods will, but onely to the execution of it. 2. If he really wills the thing, he is able to work the conditions, to work effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al faith, true repentance and other graces in all, as well as he doth in ſome.</p>
               <p>But that that place in <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> and other like places cannot be underſtood of Gods will, properly taken (as Mr. <hi>P.</hi> confidently aſſerts) may be proved, 1. Becauſe then this Scripture would croſs other Scriptures; for here it is ſaid, that the Lord hath no delight in the death of a ſinner, and elſewhere it is ſaid, that he <hi>would rejoyce over wicked men to deſtroy them and root them out,</hi> Deut. 28.63. and he would <hi>laugh at their calamity, and mock when their fear cometh,</hi> Prov. 1.25. which expreſſions ſhew, that theſe things are not againſt his will.</p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:37966:29"/>
               <p n="2">2. Theſe things are works of his Juſtice, and his Juſtice being an attribute as eſſential to him as his mercy, he muſt needs be well pleaſed, not onely with the works of his Mercy, but of his Juſtice, for all his works are well pleaſing to him.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He is well pleaſed with all things which make for his own glory, but at laſt he ſhall have much glory from the juſt deſtruction of wicked men.</p>
               <p n="4">4. If a deſire of all mens ſalvation be properly in God, then it is perpetually in him; then when wicked men are damned in hell, he ſtill continues to deſire their ſalvation, and for want of enjoying his deſire, he is hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred from enjoying full felicity (for what is full and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect felicity, but a full and perfect fruition of all our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires?) ſo that ſo long as wicked men ſuffer pains in hell, God cannot enjoy full felicity in heaven, but rather ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers ſome kinde of trouble and diſquiet, for it is a trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome thing for one, to have that perpetually withheld from him, which he earneſtly deſires. Theſe are mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous conſequences, yet ſuch as directly follow from that doctrine which teacheth, That when God ſaith, he hath no pleaſure in the death of a ſinner, this muſt be taken properly without any figure. To conclude, there is this difference betwixt theſe two wills, that God by his ſecret will and purpoſe, determines what himſelf will do, by his revealed will declares to us what is our duty to do.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> But may God command a man to do that which he doth not intend he ſhall do?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> He may: for commands are not onely for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance, but for tryal: thus he commanded <hi>Abraham</hi> to kill his ſon, when he did not intend it ſhould be done. Gods commands are not alway given to declare his ſecret intentions, but to be the rule of our actions: yea he may by his outward diſpenſations carry himſelf in a differing, yea in a contrary way to his inward intentions: He by his Prophet bade <hi>Hezekiah</hi> ſet his houſe in order, for he
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:37966:30"/>ſhould die, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 38.1. when he did not intend he ſhould die, till divers years after. He ſent <hi>Moſes</hi> to <hi>Pharaoh</hi> to command him to let the people go, when at the ſame time he tells him, that <hi>he would harden</hi> Pharaohs <hi>heart, that he ſhould not hearken to him, Exod.</hi> 7.2, 3, 4. It is not neceſſary that <hi>finis operis &amp; operantis,</hi> ſhould be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the ſame in God. The Preaching of the Goſpel in its own nature tends to life and ſalvation; but it is not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that God ſhould intend the ſalvation of all thoſe to whom the Goſpel is preached, for then it could not be a ſweet ſavor to him, not onely in thoſe that are ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, but in thoſe that are loſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.21. Mr. <hi>P.</hi> bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſerts, That there is an intention in God, to ſave all men without exception, if by the wickedneſs of their wills they did not fruſtrate his intention. But doth not this exceedingly derogate from Gods omnipotency and infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite wiſdom?
<note place="margin">Cap. 3. Pag. 81.</note> From his Omnipotency, in that he ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſires that which he is not able to effect; from his Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, in that he ſeriouſly intends that which he knows ſhall never be effected.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:37966:30"/>
            <head>AN EXAMINATION AND CONFUTATION Of the Doctrine of <hi>Conditional and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>NOt onely the old Arminians, but ſome who ſeem to diſclaim their Doctrine, yet hold, That Chriſt hath died for all mankinde, and by his death hath made ſatisfaction for all, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed pardon and ſalvation for every particular man and woman in the vvorld, upon condition they vvill believe.</p>
            <p>That this Doctrine is not agreeable to Scripture, may thus be proved:</p>
            <p>IT hath been already proved,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>1</label> That there is no Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Election of all: Novv if there be no Conditional Election of all, there is no Conditional Redemption of all, for both theſe are commenſurate, and of equal ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent one vvith another, having one and the ſame ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equate object. Chriſt hath redeemed none but thoſe vvhom the Father hath Elected, Redemption being the proper effect and fruit of Election; and the effect cannot exceed the vertue of the cauſe: If therefore the Father hath not elected all upon any condition, neither hath the Son redeemed all upon any condition vvhatever.</p>
            <p>That Redemption is the effect of Election, may thus be proved:</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:37966:31"/>
            <p n="1">1. Our Savior ſaith, That the Father had given him <hi>power over all fleſh, to give eternal life to thoſe whom he had given him,</hi> Joh. 17.2. this giving muſt be underſtood either of gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving by election or effectual calling; but it cannot be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of calling, becauſe that follows election, as a fruit of it. <hi>Thoſe whom he predeſtinated, thoſe he hth called,</hi> Rom. 8.30. And our Savior ſaith afterwards, that he had <hi>declared his Name to thoſe whom the Father had given him;</hi> verſe 6. and hereby called them; As this muſt be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, as of the elect, ſo of them onely, otherwiſe our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vior would have ſaid, Thou haſt given me power over all fleſh, to give eternal life to all fleſh; but he ſaith not ſo, but to <hi>give eternal life to thoſe whom thou haſt given me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It is ſaid that we are elected in Chriſt, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.4. In Chriſt, not the cauſe of our Election, but of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption; this being in effect the ſame with that 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.9. We <hi>are appointed to obtain ſalvation by Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</hi> So that not onely our ſalvation, but Chriſt alſo the Author of it, are made ſubordinate to our ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: and as our ſalvation, ſo alſo the giving of Chriſt, and all thoſe benefits which he hath purchaſed, are made the effects of our election, and therefore can reach no further, nor be extended to no more perſons, then to the objects of Gods electing love.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is ſaid, that by Chriſt we have <hi>Redemption through his blood, according to his rich grace,</hi> Epheſ. 1.7. which rich grace is the ſame which before he called the good pleaſure of his will; <hi>He hath predeſtinated us to be adopted through Jeſus Chriſt, according to the good pleaſure of his will,</hi> verſe 5. Election therefore is the firſt fountain whence all the benefits belonging to our ſalvation do flow, and both Adoption, Redemption and all the reſt are included in that.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Our Savior ſaith, That <hi>God ſo loved the world, that he gave his Son,</hi> John. 3. Here Gods love is made the cauſe of his giving his Son; and that this muſt be underſtood of his electing love, appears,</p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:37966:31"/>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe it is more then a common love, it is a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial peculiar love, for it is ſaid, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, he ſo loved, and this particle denotes a peculiar ſpecial love; as when it is ſaid, if <hi>God hath ſo loved us,</hi> 1 John 4.11. (if he hath ſo loved us more then others) <hi>we ought to love one another:</hi> And when he tells the Iſraelites, that he had given them his <hi>Statutes and Ordinances,</hi> and <hi>had not dealt ſo with any Nation,</hi> Pſal. 147. laſt; here is ſomething held forth pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to them above other Nations.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is ſuch a love as tends to eternal life; therefore electing love.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Such a love as cauſed Chriſt to lay down his life, and this is the greateſt love, <hi>John</hi> 15.13. therefore ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting love.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But the world is here made the object of this love, therefore it cannot be underſtood of electing love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This place is indeed uſually made to be one of the ſtrong holds for the Arminian Doctrine, but being rightly examined, it ſhall (I hope) appear to be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If the world be taken in a general ſenſe, we ſhall make every particular man and woman living in the world, to be objects of Gods ſpecial love, which croſſeth that which the Apoſtle ſaith of <hi>Eſau,</hi> that he was an object of hatred, and denies that there are any veſſels of wrath in Gods everlaſting purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is no neceſſity at all why this word ſhould be taken in a general ſenſe, including all the men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in the world: For 1. The world moſt properly ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies the whole work of Creation, the frame of heaven and earth, as when it is ſaid that God made the world. 2. All mankinde living in the world, ſo it is ſaid, God will judge the world; yea, thus it includes not onely men, but ſpirits. 3. It ſignifies not onely the whole, but a part of mankinde: and becauſe the worſt part is the greateſt part, it is frequently taken for the worſt part; thus Chriſt tells his Diſciples, that <hi>the world would hate them,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:37966:32"/>becauſe he had choſen them out of the world,</hi> John 15.19. And if the worſt part be often called the world, why may not the better part be ſometime ſo called? We uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally call that a heap of Wheat, wherein there is more chaff then Wheat: Doth not our Savior ſpeak of a world to which he gives life, <hi>John</hi> 6.33. Doth not the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeak of a reconciled world, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.15. of a world that ſhall not have their ſins imputed to them, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19. If Satan be called the Prince of this world, may there not be a world whereof Chriſt is Prince? Why may there not be a world of godly, as well as a world of ungodly? 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. as there is a whole world that lies in the ſtate of wickedneſs, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.19. Why may not there be a whole world that is brought into the ſtate of righteouſneſs? Why may not the better part (though the leſſer) be called the world, as well as they are called <hi>all fleſh,</hi> Joel 2.28. Luke 3.6. <hi>All nations,</hi> Pſal. 72.11. <hi>All the earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tract. 87. in Johan.</note> Zech. 14.9. <hi>Mundus Eccleſia eſt, &amp; totus mundus perditionis odit mundum redemptionis</hi> (ſaith <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi>) The world is the Church, and the whole periſhing world hates the redeemed world: There may therefore be a redeemed world as well as a periſhing world, a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving world as well as an unbelieving.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But World is here diſtributed into believers and unbelievers, and if it ſignifies the elect, and the elect be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers onely have everlaſting life, what ſhall become of the other?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The words do not enforce any diſtribution, for our Savior ſpeaks indefinitely, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, every be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever, every elect one when he comes to be a believer.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If a diſtribution be granted, there is no ſuch abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity in it, as <hi>J. G.</hi> would make it: For are there not two ſorts of elect in the world, ſome uncalled, others called? Thoſe that are uncalled, do yet remain in the ſtate of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief; thoſe who are called, have faith wrought in them, whereby they are fitted for everlaſting life: thoſe who are uncalled, our Savior calls by the name of the world,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:37966:32"/>becauſe they are like the reſt of the world, as yet remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the ſtate of unbelief: yet then are they the objects of Gods love, and ſheep of Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 10.16. the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he calls believers: in the firſt, he ſhews what condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion men are in, when God is pleaſed firſt to manifeſt his love to them; in the other, he ſhews what condition they ſhall be in when they come to partake of everlaſting life, they ſhall be believers, they ſhall be called, and ſo have effectual faith wrought in them.</p>
            <p>Thus we ſee how this Scripture may be vindicated from Arminian quirks and cavils.</p>
            <p>There are many to whom Chriſt will profeſs at the laſt day that he never knew them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.23.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>2</label> If he never knew them, he never died for them; for this knowledge cannot be underſtood of a knowledge of apprehenſion (becauſe ſo he knew all men in the world) but of a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of approbation and affection, a knowledge of love and liking, ſuch a knowledge as the Pſalmiſt ſpeaks of when he ſaith, The Lord knoweth the way of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.6. Now if he never loved them, he never di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for them: For Chriſts love is the ground of giving himſelf for any; he hath loved his Church, and given himſelf for it, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.25. Yea, the laying down of his life, is the act of the greateſt love, <hi>John</hi> 15.13. Yea thoughs they had prophecyed and caſt out devils, and done many other good works, yet he tells them, that he never owned them for his.</p>
            <p>If Chriſt died to purchaſe ſalvation for all,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>3</label> upon condition that they would believe, then he came to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe ſalvation for many who were already damned when he died to purchaſe ſalvation for them: But is there any poſſibility for thoſe who are actually damned, to believe and be ſaved? and is it not ridiculous to ſay that Chriſt died to purchaſe heaven for them who were already in hell, upon condition that they would believe?</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>Why might not Chriſt purchaſe ſalvation for thoſe who were actually damned, upon condition they would
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:37966:33"/>have believed, as well as purchaſe ſalvation for ſome who were actually ſaved?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The caſe is altogether unlike; for the ſalvation of thoſe who were actually ſaved, was decreed of God, and that from all eternity; for he decreed that all his elect ſhould be ſaved, and that his Son by his death ſhould purchaſe ſalvation for them, and that his death and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering ſhould be effectual to that end, even for thoſe of them who ſhould die before Chriſt himſelf actually dyed (he being in Gods decree, <hi>the Lamb ſlain from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the world</hi>) whereas it was quite contrary with thoſe who were damned; for (according to their own do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine) theſe were abſolutely decreed to be damned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were actually damned, and this decree was grounded upon the foreſight of their final infidelity and impenitency. So that it was very congruous that Chriſt ſhould die to purchaſe ſalvation for all thoſe whom God had decreed ſhould be ſaved (whether they died before or after Chriſts coming) but altogether abſurd, that he ſhould do this for thoſe who were actually damned, and this by an abſolute decree, for the conditional decree (as they teach) is always expired before execution of the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folute decree.</p>
            <p>If Chriſt died to purchaſe faith,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>4</label> and all other things needful for the ſalvation of thoſe for whom he died, then he did not die to purchaſe ſalvation for them upon condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that they would believe, and do other things to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> themſelves for it; for as he abſolutely determined to give himſelf to death, ſo alſo he abſolutely determined to purchaſe ſalvation it ſelf, and all things belonging to it, for thoſe for whom he died.</p>
            <p>That Chriſt hath purchaſed both faith and all other things needful for ſalvation, is clear from Scripture. The Apoſtle ſaith, that <hi>God the Father hath bleſſed us with all ſpiritual bleſſings in heavenly places in and through Chriſt,</hi> Epheſ. 1.3. That <hi>for Chriſt it is given to us to believe, Phil.</hi> 1.29. and it is ſaid, that he was raiſed up to
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:37966:33"/>give not onely <hi>remiſſion of ſin, but repentance to his people,</hi> Acts 5.31. and that the Father, <hi>who hath not ſpared to give his Son to death, together with him will give all things alſo,</hi> Rom. 8.32. That Chriſt by his Divine power hath <hi>given us all things which belong to life and godlineſs,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.3.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>Though Chriſt hath purchaſed Faith and other graces for us, yet he hath not done this abſolutely, but upon condition we will do that which we ought to do, in receiving what he ſhall give.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> There can be no condition deviſed or thought upon, on which Chriſt hath purchaſed, or God will give faith to thoſe that want it, but it will be the ſame, <hi>cum re conditionata,</hi> with the thing conditioned for; the ſame in effect with believing: when they ſay that God will give a man faith upon condition that he will not reſiſt his call to believe, that he will not diſdain to do what he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, that he will bend his minde and will to believe: What are all theſe in effect, but to believe? For where there is a yielding to his call, a right regard of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, a bending of the minde and will to do what he would have us; there are ſome degrees of faith, there is ſome meaſure of believing: So that it is as much a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> if they ſhould ſay, God will give them faith upon condition that they have it already; or if men do believe, God will give them the grace whereby they may believe: And is not this ridiculous?</p>
            <p n="2">2. How can it ſtand with the wiſdom of Chriſt, to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe faith or ſalvation for men, upon condition that they will do that vvhich he knovvs is as impoſſible for them to do, as it is for a Blackmore to change his skin, or a Leopard his ſpots?</p>
            <p>All theſe are vital actions, and therefore not poſſible to be performed by one that lies dead in ſins and treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes; all theſe are degrees of coming to Chriſt, and himſelf ſaith, that no man (not onely doth, but) can come to him, except the Father dravv him.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:37966:34"/>
            <p n="3">3. When the Lord hath promiſed his people that he will <hi>give them a new heart, and a new ſpirit,</hi> Ezek. 36.26. (which is a principal branch of the New Covenant) this promiſe is made abſolutely without any condition, and in this promiſe Faith is included, for a new heart is a belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving heart: though pardon of ſin, and ſalvation be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed upon our believing and repenting, yet there is no ſuch condition propounded in the promiſe of giving the firſt grace, of giving a new heart, which is a believing heart. What condition or gracious qualification can we conceive of, that ſhould precede the firſt grace, which is the ground whence all other graces do ariſe? or if there could be any ſuch gracious qualification, yet this alſo would be a part of Chriſts purchaſe, by whom we come to partake of all things that belong to life and godlineſs, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Although the performance of ſome conditions be neceſſary for thoſe who will partake of ſalvation, yet theſe were not neceſſary for the purchaſe of it; for as Chriſt knew abſolutely who ſhould be ſaved, ſo he did abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly purchaſe both ſalvation it ſelf, and the conditions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to it for all theſe, and theſe onely. Hence it is ſaid, that <hi>he with one offering hath for ever perfected thoſe that are ſanctified,</hi> Heb. 10.14. He hath made both per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſatisfaction, and a perfect purchaſe of ſalvation, and all things belonging to it, for all thoſe whom God in his eternal purpoſe hath ſet apart and ſevered from the reſt of the periſhing world, whereby in due time they come to be made perfect. To conclude; There can be no condition on mans part but what is in nature, and ſo pure Pelagia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm, for nothing but nature, before faith and repentance; and to ſay that Chriſt died for all men, to purchaſe ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for them upon condition they will do what they ought to do in receiving what he ſhall give, is to reſolve all into nature.</p>
            <p>Chriſt by his death hath taken away all thoſe things which are the great hinderances of our ſalvation,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>5</label> as infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity, impenitency, and ſuch like: therefore he abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:37966:34"/>intended the ſalvation of all thoſe for whom he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; This may be thus proved:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Chriſt by his death hath taken away all ſin, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.29. therefore theſe ſins: <hi>The blood of Jeſus Chriſt cleanſeth us from all ſin,</hi> 1 John 1.7. <hi>He hath redeemed us from all ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,</hi> Tit. 2.14.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If he did not take away all ſin, he ſhould not be a perfect Savior: he hath his denomination of Jeſus from this, that he ſhould <hi>ſave his people from their ſins,</hi> Mat. 1. yea, from all their ſins. He were not a perfect Redeemer if he ſhould deliver us out of the power of ſome enemies, and leave us in the hands of others: our ſinful luſts are our worſt enemies, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.11. It is ſaid that <hi>he hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered us out of the hands of our enemies,</hi> Luke 1.74. This is ſpoken indefinitely without limitation, and therefore taken generally for all, <hi>verſe</hi> 71. and the end of this is, That we might ſerve our God in righteouſneſs and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which we cannot do ſo long as we remain under the power of any of them; our enemies within being as hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and dangerous as thoſe without.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If he ſhould not remove thoſe hinderances that ariſe from our ſelves, no man could be ſaved, and ſo Chriſt ſhould die in vain. For as one man reſiſts, ſo would all men do, it being the eſſential property of the fleſh to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the ſpirit, <hi>and luſt againſt it,</hi> Gal. 5.17. and <hi>whatever is born of the fleſh, is fleſh,</hi> John 3.5. as before was ſhewed.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Neither can Chriſt be ſaid feriouſly to deſire the ſalvation of thoſe, and to give his life to purchaſe it, from whom he will not remove thoſe things which he certainly knows will hinder their ſalvation, when he hath power to do it.</p>
            <p>It will therefore be in vain here to except, that Chriſt would take away their unbelief if they would not reſiſt: for he takes away this reſiſtance, he takes away both care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs neglect and proud contempt, and what ever elſe can be thought of that may be a hinderance of the ſalvation of thoſe whom he intends to ſave; for he takes away all
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:37966:35"/>ſin. In the Covenant of Grace the Lord hath promiſed that he will <hi>take away the heart of ſtone:</hi> This heart of ſtone includes in it not onely a ſenſeleſs hardneſs, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief, pride, perverſneſs, ſtubbornneſs, rebellion, wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or what ever elſe we can think of, that is moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the work of Grace in our ſouls; as <hi>every valley ſhall be filled,</hi> ſo <hi>every mountain ſhall be made plain,</hi> Luke 3.3. ſo that all hinderances ſhall be removed.</p>
            <p>All thoſe whom Chriſt hath redeemed,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>6</label> 
               <hi>he purgeth them to be a peculiar people to himſelf, zealous of good works,</hi> Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus 2.14. <hi>he purgeth their conſcience from dead works,</hi> Heb. 9.14. But all are not made Chriſts peculiar people, all have not their conſciences purged; <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Object. <hi>Theſe and other like places are not to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of all thoſe for whom Chriſt hath made ſatisfaction, but onely of ſuch as have made application of it to themſelves by believing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> But here is no mention at all of mans action in applying, but onely of Chriſts action in purchaſing, and of the certain effect of it; <hi>He hath given himſelf to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>His blood purgeth the conſcience,</hi> &amp;c. 2. Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is a neceſſary effect of Redemption, for all thoſe for whom Chriſt hath made ſatisfaction, ſhall in due time partake of the benefit of it, and have this ſatisfaction ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to them: application being Chriſts work more then mans, and for whom he hath done the firſt, he will do the other alſo; which is thus proved:</p>
            <p n="1">1. If Chriſt onely ſhould make ſatisfaction, and leave it to man to make application, this work would never be done, and ſo his death would be in vain. For application is made by believing, and to believe is <hi>to come to Chriſt,</hi> John 6.35. and man hath no power to do this (as before was ſhewed) <hi>No man can come,</hi> &amp;c. verſe 44.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Apoſtle makes this to be the end why God ſent his Son into the world, namely, that he might <hi>redeem thoſe who were under the Law, that they might receive the ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of ſons,</hi> and <hi>becauſe they are ſons, God ſends the Spirit
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:37966:35"/>of his Son into their hearts,</hi> Gal. 4.4, 5, 6. Here the Spirit of adoption (whereby we are enabled to make applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) is made the effect of adoption, and adoption is made the effect of redemption, and both theſe the effect of Gods ſending his Son into the world.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Satisfaction and interceſſion are inſeparably joyned together. <hi>We have an advocate, even Chriſt the juſt, who hath made propitiation for our ſins,</hi> 1 John 2.1, 2. Why is he an advocate to plead for us, but becauſe he hath made propitiation for our ſins by his ſuffering? He prayes for all thoſe, and onely for thoſe whom the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath given him, <hi>John</hi> 17.9. and the thing which he prayes for, is, That they may partake of the benefit of his death, <hi>verſe</hi> 21, 24.</p>
            <p>The firſt and grand promiſe wherein Chriſt and the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of grace is held forth, is not made to all,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>7</label> but onely to the ſeed of the woman, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. <hi>The ſeed of the woman ſhall break the ſerpents head.</hi> Whence ariſeth this Argument: All thoſe for whom Chriſt died, for them and in them he breaks the ſerpents head, he over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwes and deſtroyes Satans power, rule and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion: But there are many in whom and for whom, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans power and dominion is never overthrown, for they live and die in a ſtate of darkneſs, remaining under the power of Satan; therefore there are many for whom Chriſt never died.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Serpents head is onely broken for, in and by the ſeed of the woman, namely, true believers; <hi>Ergo</hi> Chriſt died not for all.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Againſt theſe onely Satan may be ſaid moſt properly to exerciſe his enmity; <hi>Ergo</hi> theſe onely, and not all men, are that ſeed by whom Satan is quelled.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>By the ſeed of the woman is meant all mankinde, and by the ſeed of the Serpent are meant evil ſpirits, for the ſeed muſt be of the ſame nature with him from whom it proceeds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If ſeed be taken properly for natural ſeed, ſo
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:37966:36"/>Satan hath none: (for Spirits do not propagate) if figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratively or morally, ſo wicked men are his ſeed: Hence our Savior tells the wicked Jews, that they were <hi>of their father the Devil,</hi> John 8.44. <hi>becauſe they did his works:</hi> and the Apoſtle ſaith, that <hi>he that committeth ſin is of the Devil,</hi> 1 John 3.9. Wicked men are called Satans ſeed, not in regard of their ſubſtance, but of thoſe venemous qualities whereby they reſemble him.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>The promiſe of breaking the Serpents head is made to all upon condition that they will believe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> There is no condition at all mentioned in the Text; neither is there any thing ſpoken of mans duty, what he ſhould do, but of Chriſts work, and what he would do: here is no exhortation, but a promiſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This promiſe ſhould be made to no purpoſe, if to ſuch as are in no ſort able to fulfil the condition; yea to thouſands who never heard of promiſe or condition.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Infidelity is a principal part of Satans rule &amp; dominion, then the promiſe ſhould be made to free men from Satans rule and dominion, upon condition that they were free already, and to free them from infidelity, upon conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that they were not unbelievers: which is, as if a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian ſhould promiſe to procure health to a ſick man, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on condition that he were not ſick: A ſick man indeed is not able to heal himſelf, yet he is willing to be healed; but a ſick ſinful man is ſo ſick, as he is alſo dead in ſin, and therefore doth not ſo much as deſire to be healed, which makes his diſeaſe ſo much more deſperate.</p>
            <p>If Chriſt did ſo deſire the ſalvation of all men,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>8</label> as to give his life to purchaſe it, then he would take order that they might enjoy the means, without which this cannot be obtained; but he denies to a great many the means that are neceſſary for ſalvation. No wiſe man that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly deſires the end, will withhold the means when it is in his power to afford them; but that the means which are abſolutely neceſſary to ſalvation, are denyed to many, may thus appear:</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:37966:36"/>
            <p n="1">1. They are denyed to all thoſe infants that are born without the Church, whoſe Parents being without the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, can convey no benefit of it to their children; theſe never refuſed any offer, for it was never made to them, or if it had, they are altogether uncapable of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving any benefit by it. How can it ſtand with good ſenſe, to ſay that Chriſt died to purchaſe ſalvation for thouſands of Pagans and Infidels, upon condition they would not reject and refuſe him when he ſhould be offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them, when there was never any ſuch offer made, or if it had been, they never had any ability to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand or apprehend it?</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>They have rejected in their parents and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is a vain dream, which would make not onely the firſt ſin of the firſt man (who was the common root of all mankinde) but the ſin of every particular man to be imputed to his ſeed and poſterity, contrary to the Scripture which ſaith, that <hi>the ſon ſhall not bear the iniquity of the father, nor the father the iniquity of the ſon,</hi> Ezek. 18.20.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There are many thouſands both before and ſince the coming of Chriſt, that never heard of him: How many at this day of thoſe Savages both in Eaſt and Weſt <hi>Indies,</hi> and ſome parts of <hi>Africk,</hi> that never heard any thing either of the Covenant of Grace, or condition of it, or of Chriſt himſelf? And can it be ſaid with any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that Chriſt purchaſed ſalvation for theſe, upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition they would not reject him, when he offered him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf upon ſuch or ſuch conditions, when he was never in any meaſure offered to them?</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>All Nations have had the</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>by the works of Creation, neither hath he</hi> left any of theſe without witneſs, <hi>by</hi> giving them rain and fruitful ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, <hi>Acts</hi> 14.17.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is not the knowledge of God as Creator, but of Chriſt as Redeemer, that is ſufficient to bring men to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:37966:37"/>ſalvation; there is <hi>no name under heaven, but onely that bleſſed Name of Jeſus</hi> (the bleſſed perſon of Chriſt) <hi>by which men can be ſaved,</hi> Acts 4.12. This <hi>is eternal life, to know thee the onely very God, and whom thou haſt ſent, Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> John 17.3. There is no ſaving knowledge of God, but that whereby we know him to be one God in three perſons, a God reconciling himſelf unto us in Chriſt; that the Goſpel knowledge onely, and not that which comes by works of creation or providence, is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to bring men to ſalvation, may thus be proved.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Apoſtle ſaith, That the <hi>Goſpel is the power of God to ſalvation,</hi> Rom. 1.16. it is the onely powerful means to bring men to ſalvation: And <hi>if the Goſpel be hid, it is hid to them that are loſt,</hi> 2 Cor. 4.3. Hence it is called the <hi>ſalvation of God,</hi> Acts 28.28. that without which we cannot be ſaved: Now the Goſpel is a <hi>myſtery that hath been hid from all ages and generations,</hi> Col. 1.26. no man can be ſaved but by faith, and this <hi>faith comes by hearing,</hi> Rom. 10.17. This is that <hi>immortal ſeed whereby we muſt be born again,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.23, 25. and unleſs we be born again, we cannot enter into the kingdom of God: Hence the Apoſtle ſpeaking of thoſe Gentiles that lived without the knowledge of the Goſpel, ſaith, they were <hi>aliens from the promiſe, they had no hope, they were without God in the world,</hi> Eph. 2.12. they were <hi>ſtrangers from the life of God,</hi> cap. 4.18. <hi>they were in darkneſs, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the power of Satan,</hi> Acts 26.18. and can people that are in darkneſs and under the power of Satan, that are ſtrangers from the life of God, and are without God in the world, and have no hope of ſalvation; can theſe be in the ſtate of ſalvation, unleſs by the Goſpel they be brought out of the darkneſs unto light, and from the power of Satan to God? can theſe be ſaved without a miracle?</p>
            <p n="2">2. If the works of Nature were ſufficient to bring men to the true knowledge of God in Chriſt, then Nature ſhould be a Preacher of Evangelical Grace as well as the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:37966:37"/>Goſpel; and theſe two ſhould differ onely <hi>gradu, non ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,</hi> in degree onely and meaſure, and not in kinde and maner of manifeſtation. Did ever any Orthodox Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine in any age of the Church, once dream that the Sun, Moon and ſtars, the Trees and Plants, the Corn and Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, Oxen, Sheep and ſuch like, ſhould be preachers of Evangelical Grace?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Man had this means of knowledge before the fall, therefore this is not the way which God uſeth to bring men to the knowledge of his grace in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>The Apoſtle ſaith, that the</hi> bountifulneſs and goodneſs of God leads men to repentance; <hi>and where there is true repentance, there ſhall be remiſſion, and ſo ſalvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Though theſe in their nature tend to this end, yet it cannot be made to appear that theſe alone ever brought forth this effect, and that by them onely any man was brought to repentance unto life; they may be ſufficient means for conviction, and to render men unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable, as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.1. but not for conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: Repentance is the gift of God, <hi>Acts</hi> 11.18. which grace he conveys to men by his word, as the proper means of effecting it, and not by his works alone without his word: <hi>The law of the Lord is perfect, converting the ſoul,</hi> Pſal: 19.7. He <hi>commanded the Goſpel to be preached to turn men from darkneſs to light, &amp;c.</hi> Acts 26.18.</p>
            <p>Thus we ſee that there are many who never had ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent outward means of ſalvation; and it is evident that this came to paſs by divine diſpenſation: for the Pſalmiſt ſaith, that <hi>he gave his word unto</hi> Jacob, <hi>his Statutes and Ordinances unto Iſrael, and that he hath not dealt ſo with any Nation,</hi> Pſal. 147.19. Our Savior forbade his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples preaching to the Gentiles, and the Spirit forbade <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> to preach the word in <hi>Aſia,</hi> Acts 16.6. Now if either the Father had intended, or Chriſt had purchaſed ſalvation for all, upon condition that they would believe, they would never have withheld the means of faith from them: How <hi>can they call on him on
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:37966:38"/>whom they have not believed,</hi> and <hi>how ſhall they believe as him of whom they have not heard?</hi> Rom. 10.14.</p>
            <p n="3">3. There are many that enjoy ſufficient outward means, yet God doth not beſtow upon them inward grace, or that efficacious work of his Spirit, without which all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward means will be ineffectual. The Iſraelites that came out of <hi>Egypt</hi> wanted no outward means, for beſides the teaching of <hi>Moſes,</hi> they had ſeen all the miracles and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders which God wrought in <hi>Egypt</hi> at the Red-ſea, and in the wilderneſs, and yet it is ſaid, that God had <hi>not given them a heart to perceive, and eyes to ſee even to that day,</hi> Deut. 29.3.</p>
            <p>The Scribes and Phariſees, and wicked Jews wanted no outward means, for they heard Chriſts heavenly doctrine, and ſaw his wonderful miracles, and yet the myſteries of the kingdom of heaven were hid from them, when they were revealed unto babes; and this was done according to Gods good pleaſure, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.25. which certainly he would not have done had he intended their ſalvation, or ſent his Son to purchaſe it; our Savior ſaith that no <hi>man can enter into the kingdom of heaven unleſs he be born of water and the ſpirit,</hi> John 3.5. and this winde blows not every where, but <hi>where it liſteth,</hi> verſe 7.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>Where ever God ſends his word it is accompanied with ſuch a work of his ſpirit as is ſufficient for ſalvation, if men did not reſiſt it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. It can never be proved, that where ever God ſends his word, it is accompanied with the work of his Spirit in every one that hears it. What work had the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit upon thoſe hearers, whoſe hearts our Savior compares to the high-way ſide, where the ſeed was wholly loſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing either troden under foot, or carried away by the fowls of the air?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Though there may be ſome common work of the Spirit upon the hearts of ſuch who are never ſaved, yet not ſuch a work as is fit to bring them to ſalvation; for how can that grace be accounted ſufficient for ſalvation,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:37966:38"/>which doth not remove that which hinders mens ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and which if it be not removed it is impoſſible for them to be ſaved? if the ſtrength of that natural corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption be not removed, and the power of that rebellious diſpoſition ſubdued, which makes us alway ready to reſiſt the word of God, and the work of his Spirit, it is not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for any man to be ſaved: and if God ſhould give ſuch an efficacious grace to all men, as would be ſuperior to corruption, as would ſubdue and conquer it, then all men would be ſaved; and if it be not ſufficient to remove that which neceſſarily hinders ſalvation, it is not a grace ſufficient for ſalvation. Now how can God be ſaid ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to intend the ſalvation of ſuch from whom he with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds that without which it is impoſſible to be ſaved, when it is in his power to give it, yea he doth actually give it to all thoſe who are ſaved?</p>
            <p>Some Divines make mention of a three-fold reſiſtance, 1. There is <hi>Reſiſtentia connata,</hi> which is bred and born with a man, for whatſoever is <hi>born of the fleſh is fleſh,</hi> wherein there is a natural diſpoſition to reſiſt the Spirit, as being contrary it. 2. <hi>Reſiſtentia adnata,</hi> a readineſs to put forth this into act, when ever it meets with that which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to it ſelf. 3. <hi>Reſiſtentia vincens,</hi> a conquering reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; and this effectual grace always ſubdues and removes in thoſe whom God intends to ſave.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But God hath given every man power to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve if be will, for he hath given him an underſtanding whereby he is able to apprehend that object which is clearly propounded to him, and a will that is fit and ready to follow the dictate of his underſtanding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. This Objection preſuppoſeth that a man is able to underſtand the things of God, which is contrary to ſcripture, that telleth us <hi>the natural man doth not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the things of God, neither can he, for they are ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually diſcerned,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.14. His underſtanding is not onely darkned, but alſo overſpread with ſpiritual blinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: <hi>thou knoweſt not that thou art poor and blinde,</hi> Rev.
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:37966:39"/>3.17. the eyes of his ſoul are cloſed, and he muſt firſt have them opened before he can ſee what is the hope of his calling, &amp;c. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.18. Let a thouſand Torches be brought into a dark room where a blinde man ſits, he can ſee never the more for the help of theſe; ſo let Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Truths be propounded never ſo perſpicuouſly and clearly to one that is ſpiritually blinde, yet he is not able to ſee them in a ſpiritual maner, to ſee them ſo as to be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with them. As the bodily eye cannot apprehend rational things, ſo the rational eye cannot apprehend ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual things, for there muſt be a ſutable proportion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the faculty and the object: the light that comes by the ſpirit to thoſe who are ſpiritually enlightned, is as ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifically different from the light of natural reaſon, as the light of reaſon in man is differing from light of ſenſe in brutes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It ſuppoſeth that a natural man hath free will to good, which is contrary to Scripture, which telleth that <hi>God worketh in us both to will and to do,</hi> Phil. 2.13.</p>
            <p>It is true indeed that a natural man hath a <hi>remota po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia,</hi> a remote power of underſtanding and believing ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually, becauſe he is a ſubject capable of ſaving know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and faith, but this is no more then the power that a blinde man hath to ſee, and a lame hath to walk, which they are never the better for, till the blindneſs of the one and lameneſs of the other be removed, and they be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to act according to thoſe faculties and organs where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with mans nature is furniſhed.</p>
            <p>Thus we have ſeen that the Doctrine of a Conditional and General Redemption, is ſuch as cannot agree with Scripture; it follows now to give anſwer to ſuch Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions as are brought againſt an Abſolute and a Particular Redemption.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:37966:39"/>
            <head>AN ANSVVER TO THE OBJECTIONS That are brought againſt the DOCTRINE OF <hi>Particular Redemption.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AGainſt the Doctrine of Particular or Special Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption Mr. <hi>P.</hi> thus objects.
<note place="margin">Cap. 3. page 84.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Object. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal redemption is exhibited to us in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture by all expreſsions of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſality; by <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Collective Chriſt is ſaid to be</hi> the Savior of all men, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.10. <hi>By <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Diſtributive,</hi> he taſted death for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.9. <hi>By <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Indefinite,</hi> he is the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vior of the world, <hi>John</hi> 4.42. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Objective,</hi> he made propitiation for the ſins of the whole world, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.2. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Negative,</hi> not willing that any ſhould pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.9. <hi>by an univerſal Command to all to believe. Now if theſe places be not taken in the proper ſignification of the words, then the plaineſt places will be made moſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure: then how ſhall we be able out of Scripture to prove the Sunday Sabbath, Baptiſm, yea or the Trinity of perſons, for which there cannot be brought ſo many direct Affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Scripture, as may be brought for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. It is a very weak way of arguing, to argue from the ſignification of words, eſpecially ſuch words as have various ſignifications (as theſe have which are
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:37966:40"/>brought to expreſs the Univerſality of Redemption) as all men, every man, world, whole world, and the reſt, which are oft-times uſed, not to ſignifie every particular man and woman living in the world, but a part of them onely; as when it is ſaid that <hi>all fleſh ſhall be ſaved,</hi> Joel 2.28. Luke 3.6. That <hi>Jeruſalem and all Judea, and all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion about Jordan were baptized of</hi> John, Mat. 3.5, 6. <hi>That all that were in the ſynagogue were filled with wrath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Chriſt,</hi> Luke 4.28. <hi>That if he were let alone, all men would believe in him,</hi> John 11.48. <hi>That if he were lift up from the earth, he would draw all men unto him,</hi> John 12.32. <hi>That all that came before him were thieves and robbers,</hi> Cap. 10.8. <hi>That every one ſaith, I am of</hi> Paul, <hi>I am of</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollos, 1 Cor. 3.4. <hi>That every man ſhall have praiſe of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 4, 5. That all <hi>the world wondred after the beaſt,</hi> Rev. 13.5. That the <hi>devil deceived the whole World,</hi> cap. 12.9. That <hi>the whole world lyes in wickedneſs,</hi> 1 Joh. 5.19. to which many other might be added that ſound in the ſame maner, and yet ſignifie no Univerſality.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Scripture muſt be interpreted by Scripture, and though we are not to recede from the literal ſenſe when it will agree with other Scriptures, and with the Analogy of Faith, yet when it is defective both theſe ways, we are not bound to adhere to the letter. Now for thoſe Scriptures that carry with them a ſound of Univerſality and Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, we are enforced (if we will underſtand them aright) to take them in a limited and reſtrained ſenſe, becauſe elſe they will claſh with other Scriptures which tell us that <hi>Chriſt laid down his life for his ſheep,</hi> John 10.11. That he <hi>died to gather in one the ſons of God that were ſcattered,</hi> cap. 11.53. That he <hi>gave himſelf for his Church,</hi> Eph. 5.25. That <hi>he will not pray for the world, but for thoſe whom the Father had given him out of the world,</hi> John 17.9. <hi>That for their ſakes he ſanctified himſelf,</hi> verſe 19. That he <hi>hath redeemed us out of every people, kinred, and nation,</hi> Rev. 5.9. That there <hi>are ſome to whom he will ſay at the laſt day, he never knew them,</hi> Mat. 7.23. Now all are not
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:37966:40"/>Chriſts ſheep, all are not the ſons of God, all Nations in the world are not his Church, he will not pray for all, and therefore did not die for all: (for Redemption and Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion are of equal extent) if he hath redeemed us out of every people and nation, then he hath not redeemed all people and nations: If there be ſome to whom he will ſay that he never knew them, then he never died for them, for he did more then know thoſe for whom he died; he loved them, and that with a peculiar love, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.16. there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt take thoſe Scriptures which ſpeak in a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral way, in a reſtrained ſenſe, elſe they will not agree with theſe, neither will they agree with the Analogy of Faith; For if Chriſt hath died for all, then he hath paid a perfect price for all; if he hath paid a perfect price for all, then he hath made perfect ſatisfaction for all; if he hath made perfect ſatisfaction, then perfect juſtice requires it ſhould be accepted; if perfect ſatisfaction be made and accepted, then perfect juſtice cannot require a double payment of the ſame debt: therefore by this Doctrine all Sinners ſhould be diſcharged, and no man ſhould ſuffer in hell for his own ſin, for his debt is paid by that perfect ſatisfaction which is both made and accepted.</p>
            <p>Beſides, it cannot ſtand with Chriſts wiſdom and the infinite worth of his precious blood, that he ſhould die in vain, and ſuffer that blood to be ſpilt to no purpoſe; for when he gave himſelf to death, he certainly knew that thouſands and ten thouſands to whom he ſhould be offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, would reject him, and perſevere to the end in doing ſo, and therefore that his death would do them no good.</p>
            <p>But if the former Scriptures be taken in a limited ſenſe, they will very well agree both with other Scriptures, and with the grounds of Faith; as,</p>
            <p n="1">1. When it is ſaid that God is the Savior of all men, there is no neceſſity that word (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Savior</hi>) ſhould be underſtood of eternal ſalvation, but rather of temporal preſervation: and the foregoing words ſhew that it ſhould be ſo, which ſpeak not of Chriſt as Mediat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r, but of God
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:37966:41"/>in general; <hi>therefore we labor and ſuffer reproach, becauſe we truſt in the living God, who is the Savior or Preſerver of all, eſpecially of thoſe that believe,</hi> 1 Tim. 4.10. and this well agrees with that, <hi>the Lord preſerveth both man and beaſt,</hi> Pſal. 36.6.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When it is ſaid that Chriſt gave himſelf a ranſom for all, the former words ſhew of whom this is to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, namely, of all ſorts, of all ranks, degrees and orders of men, high and low, rich and poor, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.6. compared with <hi>verſe</hi> 2. Kings and princes were then the greateſt perſecutors, and therefore Chriſtians might doubt whether they ſhould be prayed for or not; this gave occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the Apoſtle to bid them <hi>to pray for kings and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and all that are in Authority,</hi> becauſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. When it is ſaid that Chriſt taſted death for every man, the following words ſhew of whom this every man is to be underſtood, namely, of every one of the ſons of God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.9. compared with <hi>verſe</hi> 10.</p>
            <p n="4">4. When it is ſaid that he is the propitiation for the ſins of the whole world, it hath been ſhewed before of what world this is meant, namely, the world both of Jews and Gentiles, the whole ſaved world that conſiſted of both theſe. In what ſenſe all men are commanded to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, ſhall be ſhewed by and by.</p>
            <p n="5">5. When it is ſaid that God would have none to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.9. the former words ſhew hovv it is to be underſtood, vvhere the Apoſtle ſaith <hi>that the Lord is long-ſuffering towards us,</hi> ſpeaking of himſelf and thoſe elect ones to vvhom he vvrites, that had obtained like precious faith vvith himſelf, <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>verſe</hi> 1. vvhom he oppoſeth to thoſe ſcoffers mentioned, <hi>verſe</hi> 3. and ſays that though there ſhall be a day of deſtruction of ungodly men, <hi>ver.</hi> 7. yet <hi>the Lord is long-ſuffering toward us;</hi> for it is ſo long before ſome of Gods ovvn elect come to repentance, that they have need he ſhould exerciſe much patience and long-ſuffering over them: and of theſe he ſpeaks vvhen he vvould have them <hi>account the long-ſuffering of the Lord
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:37966:41"/>to be ſalvation,</hi> verſe 15. a means to bring them to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
            <p>Here now (if we were furniſhed with Mr. <hi>P.</hi> his faculty in rhetoricating) we might retort his reaſon upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and by the ſame maner of Argumentation we might tell him, that if every particular man and woman in the world be not ſaved, if every man and woman in <hi>Judea</hi> and the coaſts round about were not baptized of <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> if every man in the world be not drawn to Chriſt, if every man in the world hath not praiſe from God, if every man in the world be not deceived by the devil, if every man in the world lyes not in wickedneſs,
<note place="margin">Cap. 3. Pag. 86. 87, 88.</note> then we ſhall make the plaineſt Scriptures moſt obſcure, and teach that God doth not ſpeak in his word as he means, and ſo teach the people to misbelieve him: becauſe theſe things are ſet forth by all expreſſions of univerſality, as all men, every man, world, yea whole world, and the like; ſo that we ſee this ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Argument is but a bladder full of winde, which being a little pricked, it preſently puffs out and vaniſheth to nothing.</p>
            <p>Object. 2. <hi>All men are commanded to believe in Chriſt, but they are not commanded to believe a lye, therefore it is true that Chriſt died for all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. All men are not commanded to believe, but thoſe onely to whom the Goſpel is preached, which is the leaſt part of the world.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The work of believing is <hi>opus complexum,</hi> ſuch a work, as to the right performance whereof many acts are required; as 1 to believe that we are loſt ſinners, and muſt periſh for ever without we have a Savior 2. That there is no ſavlation to be had, but onely in Jeſus Chriſt the Son of God that became man. 3. That it is our duty to deny our ſelves, and to reſt on Jeſus Chriſt as our onely Savior, and reſign up our ſelves to him as our onely Lord. 4. To believe that he died for our ſins, and ſhall be our Savior.</p>
            <p>Now though the Goſpel requires the doing of all theſe things, it requires they ſhould be done <hi>certo ordine,</hi> in a
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:37966:42"/>certain order. It doth not require we ſhould do the laſt without the firſt, yea if we do the laſt before we have done all the former, our believing would be a falſe believing; for if we will truly believe in Chriſt, we muſt ſo believe in him as the Goſpel holds him forth to us, otherwiſe we have no ſure ground for our faith, the Goſpel no where bids us believe that Chriſt died for all men.</p>
            <p>But Chriſt is held forth in the Goſpel onely to repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſinners, to l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt ſinners, to ſick ſinners, to humbled ſinners: when Chriſt calls thoſe onely to come to him who labor and are heavy laden, who are wearied with the burthen of their ſins, and are willing to take his yoke on them, and to them onely he promiſeth reſt: if an hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted rebellious ſinner, ſuch an one as is reſolved to walk after his luſts, and go on in his wicked ways, ſhould ſtrongly perſwade himſelf that Chriſt died for him; his ſtrong perſwaſion were no better then a ſtrong preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, the Goſpel yielding no ground at all for ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, but rather the contrary, telling us that <hi>Chriſt is the Anthor of eternal Salvation onely to thoſe that obey him,</hi> Heb. 5.9. and that <hi>he will render vengeance to all thoſe that obey not the Goſpel,</hi> 2 Theſſ. 1.8. Hence <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt (Chriſts Fore-runner) and Chriſt himſelf when they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to preach, call upon men to <hi>repent, for the kingdom of heaven is at hand,</hi> Mat. 3.2.4.17. <hi>to repent and believe the Goſpel,</hi> Mark 1.16. ſo that ſome acts of repentance are to go before believing that Chriſt died for us, which is the laſt and higheſt act of faith: Beſides, our Savior tells us that this is <hi>the condemnation of the world, that men hate the light that is come into the world, becauſe their deeds are evil,</hi> John 3.19. there is no unrepenting ſinner, but in ſome degree hates the light: ſo far as he loves his evil deeds, ſo far he hates the light (which is contrary to them) and this is the ground of his condemnation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 3. But Mr. <hi>P.</hi> objects with much confidence that of the Apoſtle,
<note place="margin">Cap. 4. page 28.</note> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14, 15. where (as he ſaith) the Apoſtle thus argues, <hi>If one died for all, then were all
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:37966:42"/>dead, but one died for all, therefore all were dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here the Apoſtle doth not onely plainly aſſert that Chriſt died for all, but brings this as a <hi>medium</hi> to prove that all were dead.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. The ſcope of the Apoſtle here is not to ſhew for how many Chriſt died, but what is the duty of thoſe for whom he died, namely, to live to him, becauſe they were in the ſtate of death when he died for them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We willingly grant that Chriſt died for all, if this word <hi>all</hi> be taken in the ſame ſenſe the Apoſtle takes it, as he takes it in the former verſe, namely, thoſe whom Chriſts love conſtrained to duty. <hi>The love of Chriſt</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>conſtraineth us,</hi> and <hi>therefore we thus judge, that if Chriſt died for all of us,</hi> then all of us were in the ſtate of death as well as others, and he died for us, that we which live ſhould no longer live to our ſelves, but to him. But it follows not hence that Chriſt died for all men, for all men are not ſo affected with the ſenſe of Chriſts love, as thereby to be conſtrained and carried on with a holy vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence as it were, to the performance of duty.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Apoſtle here ſpeaks of ſuch for whom Chriſt not onely died, but alſo roſe again; now it is no where ſaid in Scripture that Chriſt roſe again for all: beſides, if he died and roſe again for all, then all ſhall certainly be juſtified. <hi>It is God that juſtifieth, who ſhall condemn? it is Chriſt that died, or rather that is riſen again,</hi> Romans 8.33, 34.</p>
            <p>Object. 4. It is further objected, <hi>That all men in the world receive benefit by Chriſt, therefore he died for all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. It doth not follow that Chriſt died for wicked men who periſh in the end, becauſe they receive many be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits by his death: for all creatures in the world are ſome way or other the better for Chriſts death. We may well think that the whole Creation had long ſince been turned into a <hi>Chaos</hi> and confuſion, if Chriſt by his death had not made an atonement for ſome of mankinde. The Apoſtle ſaith, that the <hi>whole Creation grones under the burthen of
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:37966:43"/>mans</hi> ſin, and <hi>that there is an earneſt expectation in the creature, waiting when it ſhall be delivered from the bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of corruption, to the glorious liberty of the ſons of God,</hi> Rom. 8.21, 22. This glorious liberty of the ſons of God is a benefit which Chriſt hath purchaſed, and this all the creatures ſhall fare the better for, which makes them to have ſuch an earneſt expectation after it, yet none can hence infer that Chriſt died for all the creatures.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The devils themſelves have ſome benefit by Chriſts death, for if he had never come into the world, it is likely that they had been confined to the great deep, and not been ſuffered to range up and down in the world, as now they do. And when he was in the world, he was pleaſed at their entreaty to ſuffer them to enter into the herd of ſwine, and not to ſend them into the great deep, which was ſome benefit to them; yet who will ſay that Chriſt died for devils?</p>
            <p n="3">3. It was the act of greateſt love for Chriſt to lay down his life: <hi>Greater love then this hath no man, to lay down his life,</hi> John 15.13. and can we think that Chriſt will ſhew as great love to thoſe that are damned, as to thoſe that are ſaved; to the reprobate, as to the elect; to ſtrangers and ſuch as he never knew; yea to his enemies, and ſuch as will not ſuffer him to reign over them, as to his friends and faithful ſubjects, yea to his fellow brethren and the members of his own body? for there can be no greater love then the greateſt, and the greateſt is the laying down his life, which he hath done for all alike according to this Doctrine.</p>
            <p n="4">4. What ever comes from Love works for good; but all things in the end work together for hurt unto wicked men that have no part in Chriſt; <hi>Their table ſhall be a ſnare, and that which ſhould have been for their proſperity, ſhall be a trap,</hi> Pſal. 69.22. Their <hi>riches are reſerved for their hurt,</hi> Eccleſ. 5.9. The goodneſs of God hardens their hearts, and ſo fits them for wrath, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4, 5.</p>
            <p n="5">5. For whom Chriſt hath purchaſed a right to the things
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:37966:43"/>they enjoy, he hath alſo purchaſed a Grace that fits them for the right uſe of them; for in and through him <hi>all things are given to us that pertain to Life and Godlineſs,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.3.</p>
            <p>Object. 5. <hi>But we may ſay to any man, even the worſt that lives, if thou wilt believe, thou ſhalt be ſaved, which we could not ſay truly, if Chriſt did not die for all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. The ſcope of ſuch conditional promiſes and propoſitions, is to ſhew the inſeparable joyning together of the means and the end of Faith and Salvation, of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and Pardon of Sin; and the truth of them lies not in the truth of the parts, but in the neceſſary and ſtrong connexion and joyning of them together. As when I ſay, if a man be a lion, then he hath four feet; if he be a bird, then he can flie in the air; here though the parts be falſe, yet the propoſitions are true, becauſe of the neceſſity of the conſequence: ſo when I ſay to any man, believe and thou ſhalt be ſaved, here this propoſition is true, though the man never believes, nor never be ſaved; for let this Hypothetical be turned into a Categorical, and it is no more but this <hi>(Every Believer ſhall be ſaved)</hi> which is true, though Chriſt never died for all, and though all men never be ſaved; for it ſhews onely the abſolute and neceſſary connexion betwixt Faith and Salvation, as that all Believers, and they onely ſhall be ſaved, and not that all men ſhall be Believers, or that all men ſhall be ſaved, or that Chriſt died for all; and it doth no more imply that there is a will in God of ſaving all, then when on the other ſide it is ſaid that he who believeth not, ſhall be damned, it doth imply that there is a will in him of dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The weakneſs of this way of arguing may appear from inſtances of other like propoſitions in Scripture: when the yong man came to our Savior Chriſt, and asked him what he ſhould do that he might have eternal life? he anſwers him, <hi>If thou wilt have life, keep the command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> Matthew 19.15. did not Chriſt here ſpeak truly?
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:37966:44"/>yet it was not true that either he could keep the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, or ever ſhould have life by keeping them. Did not the Apoſtle ſpeak truly when he ſaid, <hi>If there be no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, then Chriſt is not riſen:</hi> and if <hi>there be hope onely in this life, then we are of all men moſt miſerable,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.18, 19. yet in both theſe propoſitions the parts are falſe, for both Chriſt is riſen, and there ſhall certainly be a reſurrection: and the Saints have better hopes then in this life, neither are they of all men the moſt miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. So this propoſition, If a man believe he ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, is true, though God hath never determined his ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, nor Chriſt died to purchaſe it, for ſalvation is here faſtened onely to believing, and neither believing nor ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to the man.</p>
            <p>Object. 6. Rom. 5.18. <hi>As by the offence of one man judgement came upon all to condemnation, ſo by the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onſneſs of one,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Here Chriſts righteouſneſs is made of equal extent to Adams ſin, namely, ſuch as reacheth to all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. The Apoſtle doth here parallel <hi>Adams</hi> ſin and Chriſts righteouſneſs, not in regard of their equal extent to all men in the world, but to all their poſterity. As <hi>Adam</hi> by his ſin conveyed ſin and death to all his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, ſo Chriſt by his Sufferings and Obedience con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veys Righteouſneſs and Life to all his poſterity, to all the faithful, to all true believers, who are called <hi>his ſeed,</hi> Iſa. 59.21. and <hi>his children,</hi> Heb 2.13. If there had been an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other generation of men that had not ariſen out of <hi>Adams</hi> root, they had not been involved in the guilt of <hi>Adams</hi> ſin; ſo there being a generation of men that never ſprung out of Chriſts root, that were never branches of that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Vine, they ſhall never have part in thoſe peculiar benefits, which he hath purchaſed for his children, for his ſeed and poſterity, for the members of his own body, of whom onely he is the Savior, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.23.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By this Argument all men ſhould have Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Life, and ſo all men in the end ſhould certainly
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:37966:44"/>be ſaved, for the Apoſtle ſaith expreſly in this place, that <hi>as by one mans ſin condemnation is come upon all, ſo by the righteouſneſs of one, the free gift came upon all to the juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Object. 7. <hi>The covenant of grace is univerſal, made with all mankinde, therefore Chriſt died for all, for he is the foundation of this covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. That the covenant of grace is univerſal, can never be proved; for how can Pagans and Infidels who never heard of Chriſt or covenant, be ſaid to be in cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, of whom the Apoſtle ſaith, that they <hi>are without God in the world, and are ſtrangers from the covenant,</hi> Eph. 2.12.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In the firſt promiſe wherein the covenant of grace is held forth, there is a direct diſtinction (as hath been ſhewed) betwixt the ſeed of the woman and the ſeed of the ſerpent, the promiſe being made onely to the ſeed of the woman, namely to Chriſt, and thoſe that ſhould be born of him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.13.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Apoſtle ſaith that the promiſe (wherein the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant was comprehended) was made to <hi>Abraham and his ſeed, not to ſeeds, as ſpeaking of many, but to thy ſeed, as of one, that is Chriſt,</hi> Gal. 3.16. Now if the covenant be made onely with Chriſt myſtical, head and members (as here it muſt be underſtood, becauſe the promiſe is made not onely to Chriſt, but to <hi>Abraham</hi>) it is not made with all men; all men are not <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed, all men are not members of Chriſts myſtical body, but onely believers both of Jews and Gentiles, theſe onely make that one ſeed.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In the covenant of grace the Lord promiſeth all thoſe with whom he makes this covenant, that he will <hi>give them a new heart and a new ſpirit, that he will put his laws into their inward parts, and write them in their hearts,</hi> and this promiſe is made abſolutely and without condition, and therefore ſhall certainly be fulfilled to all thoſe to whom it is made: but all men have not new
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:37966:45"/>hearts and ſpirits given unto them; therefore all are not within covenant, neither is the covenant made with all.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>All that are viſible members of the Church, that have received the Seal of the Covenant, and do ſtill own it, are in covenant; but many of theſe are ignorant, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane and wicked, therefore all that are in covenant have not new hearts and ſpirits given unto them, neither is the law of God written in their hearts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The covenant of grace may be conſidered two ways, either in regard of the outward diſpenſation and outward priviledges attending it, or in regard of thoſe inward graces which are the proper effects of it. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the outward diſpenſation, and outward privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges belonging to it, all viſible members of the Church may be ſaid to be in covenant, but in regard of the inward graces, which are the proper effects and priviledges he longing to the covenant of grace, thoſe cannot be ſaid to be in covenant, who alway remain deſtitute of them. As <hi>Abraham</hi> had a carnal ſeed who received circumciſion (which was the Seal of the covenant) and did partake of other outward priviledges belonging to the people of God, and a ſpiritual ſeed, namely ſuch as were <hi>of the faith of Abraham,</hi> ſo he hath ſtill. No man can be ſaid to be in covenant further then he knows it, and profeſſeth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to the conditions of it: wicked men may have the covenant made known to them, and make outward profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of conformity to it, and ſo have communion with the people of God in all outward ordinances, and enjoy all outward priviledges together with them, but they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not properly be ſaid to be in covenant, not partaking of the moſt eſſential parts of it, of thoſe great graces of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, Sanctification, and of Salvation in the end.</p>
            <p>Object. 8. <hi>The Apoſtle</hi> Peter <hi>ſpeaks of ſuch as</hi> denied the Lord that bought them, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2. <hi>therefore Chriſt hath died for wicked men that periſh in the end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Scripture ſometimes ſpeaks of things not onely as they are, but as they ſeem and appear to be, as
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:37966:45"/>they are in the judgements and opinions of men. Thus our Savior having ſaid in one place, that <hi>to him that hath, ſhall be given,</hi> and <hi>from him that hath not, ſhall be taken away even that which he hath,</hi> Mat. 13.12. in another place ſhews his meaning, ſaying, <hi>That ſhall be taken away which he ſeemed to have,</hi> Luke 8.18. and in this ſenſe he ſpeaks when he ſaith, <hi>that the whole have no need of the Phyſitian, but the ſick, and that he came not to call the righteous, but ſinners to repentance.</hi> And thus it is ſaid of king <hi>Ahaz,</hi> that <hi>he ſacrificed to the gods of Damaſcus that ſmote him,</hi> 2 Chr. 28.23. they did not ſo indeed, but he thought they did ſo, they ſeemed to him to do ſo, and therefore the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture ſpeaks of it accordingly: and ſo it is ſpoken in this place; theſe men had the knowledge of Chriſt, and made outward profeſſion of him and his Religion, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeemed to be ſuch as were bought and redeemed by him, but they were not ſo indeed.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
